<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Consolation in life and death wherein is shewed that interest in Christ is a ground of comfort ... begun in a funeral sermon occasioned by the death of Mrs. Ellen Asty, and since much enlarged : together with the life of the said Mrs. Ellen Asty / by Owen Stockton ...</title>
            <author>Stockton, Owen, 1630-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 241 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61649</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14523856</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14523856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102520</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61649)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102520)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1072:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Consolation in life and death wherein is shewed that interest in Christ is a ground of comfort ... begun in a funeral sermon occasioned by the death of Mrs. Ellen Asty, and since much enlarged : together with the life of the said Mrs. Ellen Asty / by Owen Stockton ...</title>
                  <author>Stockton, Owen, 1630-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 124, [2], 15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for Tho. Parkhurst ;</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The life of Mrs. Ellen Asty" has special t.p. and separate paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>CONSOLATION IN LIFE and DEATH, Wherein is ſhewed, That Intereſt in Chriſt, is a ground of Comfort under all the Troubles of Life, and Terrors of death. How they that have an Intereſt in Chriſt, may retain the ſame!</p>
                  <p>Begun in A Funeral Sermon, occaſioned by the death of Mrs. <hi>Ellen Aſty,</hi> and ſince much enlarged.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Owen Stockton,</hi> late Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel at <hi>Colcheſter</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TOGETHER With the Life of the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Ellen Aſty,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom. 8. v. 38.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>For I am perſwaded that neither Death nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom. 8. v. 39.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Nor height, nor depth, nor any other Creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns, at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1681.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>To the Worthily Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>John Clark,</hi> of <hi>Bury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk, Eſquire.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IT is your ſeriouſneſs in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, together with your intimate Acquaintance with, and reſpect for, Reverend Mr. <hi>Owen Stockton,</hi> that occaſioneth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixing your name to the enſuing Treatiſe, of which he was the Author. He was one, mighty in the Scriptures, whoſe Life was much deſired, and his Death much lamented. As you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted
<pb facs="tcp:102520:3"/>to hear him Preach when he was alive; So I doubt not, but he being dead, you are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hear him yet ſpeaking; eſpecially in a word of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the troubles of Life, and the fears and terrours of Death.</p>
                  <p>I hope the Lord hath deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ſelf from the Sting of Death, but yet you may need ſome help againſt the fear of it. Take a ſurvey of your Mercy, that you are not under the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs of Chriſtleſs Souls, who, through the fear of Death, are all their life time ſubject to Bondage.</p>
                  <p>It is ſaid, that the <hi>Indians</hi> being alarum'd with the Approaches of Death by its Arreſtment, ſo as all
<pb facs="tcp:102520:3"/>hope of recovery is paſt, then to behold and hear their throbbing ſobs, and deep-fetched ſighs, their grief-wrung hands, and tear-bedewed cheeks, their dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful cries, would draw tears from Adamantine Eyes, that be but Spectators of their mournful Obſequies.</p>
                  <p>Indeed it is unexpreſſibly ſad, to be under a Conviction (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are) of the immortality of a never dying Soul, and yet to be Strangers to the promiſe of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life. Such muſt needs be Mourners without hope.</p>
                  <p>All the Cordials in the World in this caſe, will not afford the leaſt drop of refreſhment to ſuch diſconſolate Souls: nor will a Righteouſneſs of our own be a
<pb facs="tcp:102520:4"/>ſure bottom for Comfort againſt that laſt Enemy Death.</p>
                  <p>But behold, here is a way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphered, whereby we may not only be helped to leave Riches, Friends, Wife, Children, Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Lands, and depart in peace, but alſo with exceeding joy. <hi>[In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt]</hi> will be a means to turn Death the King of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors into the King of Comforts; it will make it of a bitter Enemy, a familiar Friend, an Out-let to Affliction, and a Portal to Glory.</p>
                  <p>How that <hi>[Intereſt]</hi> conduceth to the fitting a Soul with Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, is diſcovered here, by this eminent Servant, and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Owen Stockton,</hi> in a Funeral Sermon upon the Death of Mrs. <hi>Ellen Aſty,</hi> (the
<pb facs="tcp:102520:4"/>Relict of that Reverend Mr. <hi>Aſty,</hi> late of <hi>Stratford</hi> in <hi>Suffolk</hi>) which afterwards he much enlarged, and ſo left it under his own hand. It was intended that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Stockton</hi> ſhould have printed it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with her Life; but Death arreſting him, before he had Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed that work; Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath caſt it upon my hands to draw her Portraiture out of the papers which were in his hands to that end; which I have done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and here preſent it to your ſelf, and to publick view. I muſt ſay further, that this is a Branch, or part of a Treatiſe of his, on the ſame Text, entituled <hi>[the beſt Intereſt],</hi> which probably will follow ſpeedily. This, and that together, compleat the Subject,
<pb facs="tcp:102520:5"/>yet either of them might have appeared to the Reader, as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and diſtinct Treatiſe, had I not hinted thus much.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall only add, that my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſire is, that the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, may bleſs you with all Spiritual Bleſſings in Heavenly places in Chriſt, ſo prayeth,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>September</hi> 1. 1681.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Servant in the Goſpel, <hi>Sam. Petto.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>PAge <hi>3.</hi> l. <hi>25.</hi> dele for. p. <hi>23.</hi> l. <hi>26.</hi> r. there are. p. <hi>29.</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> r. grace. p. <hi>37.</hi> l. <hi>29.</hi> dele ſhould. p. <hi>42.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> for ready r. really. p. <hi>44.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> for upon r. yea. p. <hi>59.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> for ſight r. fight. p. <hi>60.</hi> l. <hi>28.</hi> r. carried on. p. <hi>70.</hi> l. <hi>13.</hi> r. truſting. p. <hi>88.</hi> l. <hi>13</hi> for here r. how. p. <hi>96.</hi> l. <hi>17.</hi> for preſerving r. preferring.</p>
                  <p>In Mrs. <hi>Aſtys</hi> Life,</p>
                  <p>Page <hi>8.</hi> l. <hi>26.</hi> dele never. p. <hi>9.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> r. uprightneſs. p. <hi>10.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> r. never ſeemed.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102520:5"/>
                  <head>CONSOLATION IN LIFE and DEATH.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Cant. 2.16.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>My Beloved is mine, and I am his, he feedeth among the Lilies.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THis Book containeth a Diſcourſe concerning Jeſus Chriſt, and his Church. Sometimes Chriſt is brought in ſpeaking of his Church, and ſometimes, to his Church. And at other times the Church is brought in ſpeaking of Chriſt, and ſometimes to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>In this Text the Spouſe of Chriſt is brought in ſpeaking concerning Chriſt, and expreſſing her grounds of Conſolation, that ſhe had, both under the troubles of Life, and the danger of Death. The troubles of the Church are ſet out. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.6. She was <hi>black, becauſe the Sun had
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102520:6"/>looked upon her,</hi> which ſignifieth the ſcorching perſecutions, that the Lord ſuffereth to come upon the Church, to try the Faith and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his Servants. And ſhe met with much anger and hard uſage from <hi>her Mothers Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> that is, thoſe that profeſſed the ſame Faith with her ſelf, <hi>my Mothers Children were angry with me,</hi> and made me the Keepers of their Vineyards, and would not ſuffer her to keep her own Vineyard. Her troubles are further ſet out. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>As a Lilie among Thorns, ſo is my Love among the Daughters,</hi> that is, compaſſed about on every ſide with ſharp and ſore troubles, that did prick, and grieve, like Thorns, or that her lot and habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in the midſt of evil Men, who were like Thornes in her ſide. Her inward troubles are touched on, which did proceed from her abundant love to Chriſt: <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>I am ſick of love.</hi> Sickneſs makes a man reſtleſs, ſuch was her condition, a reſtleſs condition.</p>
                  <p>Her troubles are alſo ſet out, <hi>v.</hi> 15. There were Foxes abroad, that made ſpoil of the Vines. And theſe Foxes were of two ſorts.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Falſe Teachers, that did by falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine corrupt and ſpoil the Vines. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Iſrael, thy Prophets are like the Foxes,</hi> that is, <hi>the falſe Prophets;</hi> for the <hi>true</hi> Prophets ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and cheriſh the Vines, they are the falſe Prophets, that ſpoil the Vines.</item>
                     <item>2, Subtle and cruel Perſecutors, that ſeek after the lives of the Saints, are theſe Foxes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.31, 32.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102520:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. The Diviſion of the Words with the Doctrines.</p>
                  <p>In the words we have
<list>
                        <item>1. The Title given to Chriſt <hi>[my Beloved]</hi> or as the <hi>Dutch, my beſt Beloved,</hi> or as one <hi>unicè dilectus,</hi> my only Beloved. Whatever apprehenſions other men may have of Chriſt, though they ſee no beauty, or comlineſs, why they ſhould deſire him, though he be to them a ſtone of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence, though they make light of him, and reject him; yet gracious Souls love Chriſt, yea, he is their beſt Beloved; they love him above all things and perſons in the World.</item>
                        <item>2. VVe have the claim that is laid to Chriſt, <hi>My Beloved is mine.</hi> I have a ſpecial and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar intereſt in him, he is mine, as much as any thing, that I have, is mine, <hi>my Beloved is mine,</hi> I can, I do, I will lay claim to him, as my own, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.6. <hi>God, even our own God ſhall bleſs us.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. The Confidence the Spouſe had of her ſpecial and peculiar intereſt in Chriſt. It is not, <hi>I hope he is mine,</hi> or by way of deſire, <hi>O that he were mine,</hi> but it is ſpoken with much confidence, <hi>my Beloved is mine. Iſaiah</hi> 63.16. <hi>Doubtleſs thou art our Father.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. Here is Chriſts Intereſt in his Church, <hi>I am his.</hi> I am not, I will not be mine own, but <hi>I am his.</hi> I am not the Worlds, but he hath choſen and called me out of the world, <hi>I am his.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102520:7"/>
                        <item>5. Chriſts familiar converſe with his Church, <hi>he feedeth among the Lilies,</hi> that is, he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth his preſence to them, he converſeth familiarly with them, as perſons do that feed together.</item>
                        <item>6. The perſons among whom Chriſt feeds, they that are his, thoſe that love him, thoſe that reſemble the <hi>Lilies,</hi> that is, humble Souls, ſuch as walk innocently, ſuch as are fruitful. It's <hi>Plinys</hi> Obſervation, <hi>Lilio nihil faecundius,</hi> ſuch as are like Chriſt, the lilie of the Valleys, meek and lowly in heart.</item>
                        <item>7. The Conſolation the Church hath under all the troubles of this Life, and the fears of Death, and that ariſeth from two Heads.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Her intereſt in Chriſt, <hi>my Beloved is mine.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. The enjoyment of Chriſts preſence, <hi>he feedeth among the Lilies.</hi> Feeding implyeth
<list>
                              <item>1. His preſence and familiar converſe with her.</item>
                              <item>2. His delight in her, feeding ſignifieth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, John 4.34. <hi>My meat is to do the</hi> will of him that ſent me.</item>
                              <item>3. His miniſtring inward and ſpiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts. Judg. 19.5. <hi>Comfort thine heart with a morſel of bread.</hi> And inward ſupports. Pſal. 104.15. <hi>Bread which ſtrengthneth mans heart.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. Jeſus Chriſt and Gracious Souls have a mutual intereſt, each in other, Chriſt is theirs, and they are his.</item>
                                    <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102520:7"/>
                                    <item>2. Such as believe in Chriſt may come to a ſure and certain Knowledge of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, they may be able to ſay with much confidence, Chriſt is mine, and I am his.</item>
                                    <item>3. Every true Believer hath a great love to Jeſus Chriſt, yea he loveth Chriſt above all things and perſons in the whole world. My beloved, or as ſome render it, my beſt beloved.</item>
                                    <item>4. It is the work and office of Faith, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate, and apply Chriſt to a mans own Soul. My beloved is mine.</item>
                                    <item>5. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt feedeth among the Lilies, that is, converſeth with them, delighteth in them, Communicates Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comforts and ſupports to them.</item>
                                    <item>6. It is a great comfort to the Saints in an evil day, when they are as a Lilie among Thorns, that Chriſt feedeth among the Lilies.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Obſervation inſiſted on is.</p>
                  <p>Doct. <hi>Intereſt in Chriſt is a ground of ſtrong Conſolation under all the troubles of this life, and the dangers and approaches of Death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When it was a time of perſecution, and there were Thorns on every ſide, and the Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſpoyling the Vines, the Spouſe could tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in this, <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am his, Luk.</hi> 1.47. The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> went
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102520:8"/>through ſore afflictions as ſharp, as if ſhe had <hi>a Sword run through her. Luk.</hi> 2.35. yet her Spirit could rejoyce in God her Saviour. <hi>Paul</hi> when ſhut up in Priſon, could, and did rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.13. compared with <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. <hi>We rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus. Cant.</hi> 8.5. The Wilderneſs, a place of great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and a land of the ſhadow of Death, that is, where they walked almoſt continually in danger of death. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.6. yet under all the troubles of the wilderneſs, and the ſhadow of death, there was refreſhment by leaning on Chriſt. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. <hi>David</hi> was in great diſtreſs, that he wept till he could weep no more, and was in danger of death, yet he could <hi>encourage himſelf in the Lord his God. Cant.</hi> 2.2.3. As a Lilie among Thorns, yet there, <hi>I ſat down under his ſhadow with great delight. Pſal.</hi> 23.1.4. <hi>The Lord is my Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd,</hi> and what then? <hi>though I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death, I will fear no evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. VVhat is meant by an Intereſt in Chriſt? How Chriſt becomes ours, how we become Chriſts.</p>
                  <p>For the farther clearing hereof, that an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt is a ground of ſtrong Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under all the troubles of this life, and againſt the Fears and Terrors of Death, it will be expedient to enquire, what is meant by an Intereſt in Chriſt. And how Chriſt becomes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102520:8"/>ours, and how we become his. To that end we may take notice of a three fold Intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. A general intereſt which is common to all men, the evil, as well as the good, an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt by virtue of Creation, and of Chriſts being Lord of all. The, Son as well as the Father, was the Creatour of Mankind, and all other creatures. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made that was.</hi> And not only by Creation hath Chriſt a right to all Mankind, but as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour he is Lord of all, and is made Judge of the quick and dead, and hath power over all fleſh. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.36. <hi>Preaching Peace by Jeſus Chriſt, he is Lord of all, Joh.</hi> 3.35. <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loveth the Son, and hath given all things into his hands. Joh.</hi> 17.2. <hi>Thou haſt given him power over all fleſh.</hi> This general intereſt in part, as his creatures, or as ſubjects of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatory Kingdom, is not that intereſt, which is a ground of Conſolation. For he ruleth by his power in the midſt of his Enemies. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.2. <hi>Rule thou in the midſt of thine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. There is a Titular Intereſt in Chriſt, when men profeſs themſelves to be Chriſts, and profeſs, and ſay that Chriſt is theirs, but they are not his, neither is he theirs in truth. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.11. <hi>He came to his own, and his own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieved him not.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> are called Chriſts own, becauſe they profeſſed themſelves to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102520:9"/>the people of God, but many of them were not his people. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.54, 55. <hi>Ye ſay that he is your God, yet ye have not known him</hi> Many lay claim to God as their God, and to Chriſt as their Saviour, that have no real intereſt in God and Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>3. There is a ſpecial ſaving intereſt in Chriſt as our Redeemer, which is, when a man is made a partaker of Chriſt, united to Chriſt, and hath a real and actual right to all the ſaving benefits of Chriſt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14 <hi>We are made partakers of Chriſt.</hi> They that are thus Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted in Chriſt, are ſaid to be in Chriſt, and by vertue of their Union with him, they have a right to all his ſaving benefits. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and Redemption.</hi> To be thus intereſted in Chriſt is not common to all men, but it is a ſpecial priviledge belonging to a peculiar people. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and parifie unto himſelf a peculiar people.</hi> As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, we find ſome men are Chriſt owned by him for his own. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.23. <hi>ye are Chriſts; Joh.</hi> 13.1. Jeſus having <hi>loved his own, loved them unto the end.</hi> Some men are none of Chriſts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Now if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his;</hi> but are without any part or portion in Chriſt. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. <hi>At that time ye were without Chriſt,</hi> ſome men have a part
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102520:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>with Chriſt, ſome have no part at all in him or with him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.8. <hi>If I waſh thee not thou hast no part with me.</hi> To open the nature of this ſaving Intereſt in Chriſt more fully, I ſhall reſolve theſe two queſtions. 1. How Chriſt becometh ours. 2. How we become his.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>How doth Chriſt become ours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. By the Fathers giving him to be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſins, and Chriſts giving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to die for our ſins, God the Father gave Chriſt to be the propitiation for our ſins. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and ſent his Son to be the propitiation for our ſins.</hi> And as God gave Chriſt, ſo Chriſt gave himſelf to be a Sacrifice and ranſom for us. There was his own conſent to this Gift, the giving himſelf to die for our ſins. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Who loved me, and gave himſelf for me. Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Who gave himſelf for us</hi> — 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Who gave himſelf for a ranſom for all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt becomes ours by effectual calling, for when God calls us effectually, he calls us to fellowſhip with Chriſt, that is, to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chriſt, and all his ſaving benefits. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. <hi>God is faithful by whom ye were called to the Fellowſhip of his Son Jeſus Christ our Lord.</hi> When Chriſt dyed, he gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102520:10"/>for us, when we are effectually called, he giveth himſelf to us. By the death of Chriſt there was an impetration or purchaſe of all things, that were neceſſary to our Salvation. In our effectual calling there is an application of Chriſt, and all the benefits purchaſed by Chriſt to our own Souls. As ſoon as we are effectually called, Chriſt becomes ours, and all his benefits become ours, we have an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual right to an intereſt and propriety in Chriſt, and in all his ſaving benefits. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Ye ſee your calling, brethren—All are yours, and ye are Chriſts.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.23. They that are effectually called, Chriſt is theirs, and all the benefits of Chriſt are theirs. I add this word <hi>effectual,</hi> becauſe many are outwardly called by the Goſpel, who are not inwardly and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually called to Fellowſhip with Chriſt, now this effectual calling whereby we are made partakers of Chriſt, and his ſaving benefits, conſiſts of theſe three Branches.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Illumination, when God calls us effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, he brings us out of our ignorance and darkneſs, and gives us the knowledge of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Son Jeſus Chriſt. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Who hath called you out of darkneſs into his marvellous light.</hi> The knowledge of Chriſt, and God in Chriſt, is a great furtherance of our being partakers of Chriſt, and his ſaving benefits, for through the knowledge of Chriſt are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to us, all things pertaining to Life and Godlineſs. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. <hi>According as his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102520:10"/>divine power hath given us all things pertaining to Life and Godlineſs through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and vertue.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The looſening and taking off the heart from all things that hinder the Soul from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to and following after Jeſus Chriſt A man is called off from all that hinders his cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Chriſt, whether they be worldly luſts, or fleſhly luſts, or relying upon our own Righteouſneſs, or any other impediments. A man is made to leave all to enjoy Chriſt; when Chriſt called <hi>Levi,</hi> he left all for to go after Chriſt. <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.27, 28. <hi>He ſaid unto him fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me; and he left all, roſe up, and followed him.</hi> When Chriſt called <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> they left their Father, their Servants, their Ship and there Nets and all to follow Chriſt. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.20. <hi>He called them, and they left their Father</hi> Zebedee <hi>in the Ship with the hired Servants, and went after him.</hi> When the Lord had called the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> he was willing to ſuffer the loſs of all things that came in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with Chriſt, ſo that he might win Chriſt; <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Yea doubtleſs, and I count all things but loſs for the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the loſs of all things, and do count them but dung that I may win Chriſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. VVhen God calls a man effectually, he calls him to believe in Chriſt; he calls him to come to Chriſt, and to accept of Chriſt as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the Goſpel, and to rely upon him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102520:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>for his Salvation. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.45. <hi>Every man that hath heard, and learned of the Father, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto me.</hi> The Father calls us to come to his Son; and every one that heareth this call effectually cometh to Jeſus Chriſt. Now they that are thus called to the knowledge and faith of Chriſt are made partakers of Chriſt and all his ſaving benefits, for by Faith Chriſt dwells in our hearts. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by Faith.</hi> And they that are thus called, ſhall have remiſſion of ſins, and eternal life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Whom he called, them he alſo juſtified, and whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="3">3. Chriſt becometh ours by our recieving him. The Spirit of God maketh a free offer of Chriſt to every one that is willing to have him; <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. <hi>The Spirit ſaith come — And let him that is a thirſt come; And whoever will, let him take the Water of Life freely.</hi> VVhen we recieve Jeſus Chriſt thus offered to us he becometh ours, and we become his, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. <hi>To as many as recieved him, to them gave he power to become the Sons of God, even to them that believe on his name.</hi> VVhen we recieve Chriſt, he becomes our Saviour, and God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes our Father, and we become his Sons. Now this recieving Chriſt implyeth theſe 3 things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) Our recieving that Teſtimony which is given of Chriſt in the Goſpel concerning the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102520:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>perſon, offices, death, and ſufferings of Chriſt, and the benefits that we have thereby. As namely, that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> was God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the Fleſh, the Son of God, as well as the Son of man, that he is that Saviour that was foretold and promiſed ſhould come into the World to ſave loſt man, that he dyed for our ſins, and roſe again for our juſtification, and aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth at the right hand of God tomake interceſſion for us; that God hath made him both Lord and Chriſt, and exalted him to be a Prince and a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now then we recieve his Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, when we believe the truth of thoſe things which are revealed in the Goſpel concerning Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.33. <hi>He that hath receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Teſtimony, hath ſet to his Seal, that he is true.</hi> Thus we receive Chriſt, when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Doctrine of the Goſpel, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue therein. And this is neceſſary to our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying an Intereſt in Chriſt. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. <hi>He that abideth in the Doctrine of Chriſt, he hath both the Father, and the Son.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(2.) We recieve Jeſus Chriſt by the conſent of our Wills. When our Wills conſent to take this Jeſus for our Lord and Saviour, as he is offered to us in the Goſpel, and we are willing to be ruled by him, and to be ſaved by him in his own way. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Whoſoever will, let him take the water of life freely.</hi> The great work is to porſwade and bring over the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102520:12"/>will to Chriſt, to make a man willing to have Chriſt for his Lord and Saviour, and to be willing to to be ſaved by him in Life and Death in his own way. The averſeneſs of the will, to accept of Chriſt for our Lord and Saviour, we may ſee from ſuch Scriptures as theſe. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 81.11. <hi>Iſrael would none of me. Luk.</hi> 19.14. <hi>We will not have this man reign over us. Joh.</hi> 5.40. <hi>Ye will not come unto me that ye might have life.</hi> It is the work of God, yea the power of God, that is required to make a man willing to have Chriſt for his Lord and Saviour, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>It is God that worketh in you, both to will and to do, of his own good pleaſure. Pſ.</hi> 110.3. <hi>Thy people ſhall be willing in the day of thy power.</hi> When our wills conſent to take Chriſt as he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers himſelf to us, he becomes ours. As the conſenting to the enticeing of Sinners, makes us one with them, and makes us partakers of their evil deeds. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.18. 2 <hi>John ver.</hi> 11. And therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſeth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.10. <hi>My Son, if ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not.</hi> So by our conſenting to receive Chriſt, when he offers himſelf to us, and wooeth, and intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to accept him, we become one with, and are made partakers of his benefits. As 'tis in Marriage, it is not wooing and waiting, but conſenting that makes up the Match. So it is in the myſtical Marriage, it is not inviting and calling, and waiting, but conſenting makes up the Match.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102520:12"/>
                  <p n="3">3. We receive Chriſt for our Saviour, when we rely upon him, and truſt in him for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all things requiſite unto Salvation. When we look upon him as the only Saviour, and as an all-ſufficient Saviour, and do truſt in him for our eternal Salvation. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. <hi>In whom ye truſted after ye heard the word of truth, the Goſpel of your Salvation.</hi> Pſ. 86.2. <hi>O thou my God, ſave thy Servant that truſteth in thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lord was diſpleaſed with the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> when they did not truſt in his Salvation. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.21, 22. <hi>The Lord was wroth, becauſe they believed not in God, nor truſted in his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> In theſe three things conſiſteth this duty of receiving Chriſt.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. In the aſſent of the mind, to the truth of thoſe things that are revealed concerning Chriſt in the Goſpel.</item>
                     <item>2. In the conſent of the will to take this Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus for our Lord and Saviour.</item>
                     <item>3. In the relyance or truſt of the heart on Chriſt for Salvation.</item>
                     <item>4. Chriſt becometh ours, by our entring into Covenant with God. When upon the call of the Goſpel we come to Chriſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, then we enter into Covenant with God, then God makes an everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with us. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>Incline your ear, and come unto me, hear, and your ſouls ſhall live, and I will make an Everlaſting Covenant with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102520:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>you, even the ſure Mercies of David.</hi> And when the Lord takes us into his Covenant, then Jeſus Chriſt becometh ours, and all his ſaving benefits become ours. For one main branch of the covenant is to give us Chriſt and all his ſaving benefits. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. <hi>I will give thee for a Covenant of the people, for a light of the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>to open the blind eyes, and to bring out the Priſoners from the Priſon.</hi> The great promiſe of the new covenant is, <hi>I will be your God. Ezek.</hi> 36.28. And when the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to be our God, in that promiſe God the Father engageth himſelf to be our Father, and God the Son engageth to be our Saviour and our Redeemer, and God the Holy Ghoſt engageth to be our comforter.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>How do we become Chriſts.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. By the donation of the Father. God the Father choſe out of the children of men whom he ſaw good, and gave them to Jeſus Chriſt to be his peculiar people, to be redeemed and ſaved by him. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.6. <hi>Thine they were, and thou gaveſt them me.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Ye are a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen generation, a peculiar people.</hi> All that God choſe to eternal life, he gave to Chriſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them. So that all that are Chriſts are the Fathers, and all that are the Fathers by election, are the Sons by redemption. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.10. <hi>All mine are thine, and thine are mine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. VVe are Chriſts by Redemption; He bought us with a price, he purchaſed us with his own blood, he bought us Body and Soul
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102520:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>for himſelf with a great price. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 20. <hi>Ye are not your own, ye are bought with a price, therefore glorifie God in your body and in your Spirits which are Gods.</hi> The price that Chriſt gave for this purchaſe, was his own blood; <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>To feed the Church of God which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. We become Chriſts by the Spirits cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and enabling us to give our ſelves to Chriſt, We become Chriſts by a voluntary reſignation of our own ſelves unto him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Firſt gave their own ſelves unto the Lord. Iſa.</hi> 44.5. <hi>One ſhall ſay I am the Lord, and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand to the Lord.</hi> that is, ſhall ſurely and firmly engage himſelf to be the Lords Servant; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.16. <hi>O Lord, truly I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>IIII. VVe become Chriſts by vertue of the covenant. He enters into covenant with us, that he will graciouſly accept us to be his. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. <hi>I entered into a Covenant with thee, ſaith the Lord God, and thou becameſt mine.</hi> It is part of Gods Covenant that he will accept of us for his people. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Ye ſhall be to me a people.</hi> And as the Lord makes a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with us to accept us for his, ſo we make a covenant with the Lord that we will become his people, and continue his for ever. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11.17. Jehoiada <hi>made a covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lord and the King and the People, that they ſhould be the Lords People.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102520:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. Several grounds of Conſolation againſt the troubles of Life, and the fears and terrors of Death, ariſing from an intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>We have ſeen what is meant by an intereſt in Chriſt, namely an actual right to, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in Chriſt himſelf, as our Redeemer; and a right to, and propriety in all the ſaving benefits purchaſed by his Blood. VVe have ſeen alſo how Chriſt becomes ours, and how we become his. Now let us conſider what ſolid grounds of comfort we may have both againſt the fears and terrours of Death, and the troubles of Life from our Redemption by Chriſt, or from intereſt in Chriſt, and thoſe ſaving benefits which he hath purchaſed for us.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. Jeſus Chriſt hath fully, perfectly, and for ever reconciled unto God all that are his. The elect as well as others were by nature <hi>the Children of wrath. Eph.</hi> 2.3. But by the Death and ſufferings of Chriſt, they are redeemed from the wrath of God, both for preſent, and time to come. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Being now juſtified by his blood, we ſhall be ſaved from wrath through him.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 1.10. <hi>Even Jeſus which hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from wrath to come.</hi> Our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath by his Death and ſufferings fully reconciled all that are his, unto God for ever, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>Having made peace through the blood of his Croſs, by him to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile all things unto himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. All that are Chriſts, whether they be ſuch as are already in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102520:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Heaven, or ſuch as are ſtill upon the Earth, were reconciled to God by that bloud that he ſhed upon the croſs. All that are Chriſts in all ages of the world, and in all places of the world are reconciled to God by Chriſt. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world to himſelf.</hi> And as Chriſt hath reconciled all that are his unto God, ſo he hath fully and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reconciled them to God, and that for ever, by his offering up himſelf a Sacrifice to God for them. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. <hi>For by one offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath perfected, for ever them that are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</hi> I ſhall open this fulneſs and perfection of this Reconciliation in three or four parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Jeſus Chriſt by his Death hath ſo fully reconciled all that are his unto God; that he is pacified towards them, notwithſtanding all their offences, whether original or actual, and will not impute any one of their offences to them 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world unto himſelf, not imputing their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes unto them.</hi> The nature of reconciliation lyeth in pacifying God for the offence our ſins have cauſed, and this pacification Chriſt our High Prieſt hath wrought for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17. <hi>That he might be a merciful and faithful High Prieſt, in things pertaining to God, to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation for the ſins of the people.</hi> And this pacification is ſo full, that it is a pacification for all offences. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.63. <hi>I am pacified to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; thee for all that thou haſt done, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102520:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <item>2. Jeſus Chriſt hath ſo fully reconciled all that are his unto God, that God hath laid aſide all his wrath againſt them, and retaineth no fury at all againſt them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.3. <hi>Thou hast taken away all thy wrath, thou haſt turned thy ſelf from the fierceneſs of thine anger. Iſa.</hi> 27.4. <hi>Fury is not in me.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Jeſus Chriſt hath ſo fully reconciled all that are his unto God, that the Lord hath ſworn that he will be wroth with them no more. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.9, 17. <hi>This is as the waters of Noah un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, for as I have ſworn that the waters of Noah ſhould no more go over the Earth, ſo I have ſworn that I would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee. —This is the heritage of the Servants of the Lord.</hi> But ſome may ſay, are not ſome of the Servants of Chriſt chaſtned very ſorely, and do they not complain, that the wrath of God lyeth hard upon them as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Pſal.</hi> 88.7.16.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>How then is God true to his Oath, that he will be wroth with them no more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. The rebukes and chaſtnings of the Members of Chriſt, do not come from wrath, but love. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Whom I love, I rebuke and chaſten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The people of God are ſubject to miſtakes, when they judge according to ſence, and not according to what is revealed in the word of God; when they judge according to ſence and feeling, they may think many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of God, to be expreſſions of his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102520:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>wrath, which they might underſtand to be all Mercy, and to have no wrath in them, if they did judge according to Faith, and according to what they find in the word of God. For there we read that <hi>All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth unto ſuch as keep his Covenant, and his Teſtimonies. Pſ.</hi> 25.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When the Lord ſwears that he will not be wroth, nor rebuke his Servants, it is to be underſtood of Eternal wrath, that he will not rebuke them, ſo as to deſtroy, for ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking is ſometimes underſtood, namely of eternal deſtruction. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Thou haſt rebuked the Heathen, thou haſt deſtroyed the wicked, thou haſt put out their name for ever and ever.</hi> For this is like the Oath of God concerning the waters that covered the Earth in <hi>Noah's</hi> time. God hath ſworn that the VVaters ſhall no more cover the Earth to deſtroy the Earth as it did in <hi>Noah's</hi> Floud, yet notwithſtanding this Oath, God doth often chaſten the Inhabitants of the Earth, with unſeaſonable rain and flouds, but not ſuch as ſhall deſtroy the world. So when the Lord ſwears, that he will not be wrath with, or rebuke his Servants, it's of eternal wrath, of caſting them away for ever; yet he may, and often doth chaſten them, with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral chaſtiſements.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Jeſus Chriſt hath ſo fully reconciled all that are his unto God, that he hath not only pacified his Fathers Anger, but he hath reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and brought them into the love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102520:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>By whom alſo we have acceſs by Faith into this grace wherein we ſtand.</hi> By grace here is meant the love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, and by Chriſt we have not only peace with God, but acceſs into and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the grace and favour of God. By Chriſt we are brought into an higher degree of the love and favour of God, than <hi>Adam</hi> did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy while he was in innocency. For we are under a better Covenant, and have better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes than <hi>Adam</hi> had, <hi>Adam</hi> was in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, yet ſo as he was capable of loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the favour of God, and being a child of wrath; And by his fall he did loſe the love of God. But they that are Chriſts are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the love of God, that Gods loving kindneſs ſhall never depart from them. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>The Mountains ſhall depart, and the Hills be removed, but my kindneſs ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thee, nor the Covenant of my peace be removed ſaith the Lord that hath mercy on thee.</hi> And as God will not of himſelf take away his loving kindneſs, ſo neither can any creature in Hell or on Earth, ſeparate us from the love of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. <hi>I am perſwaded that neither Death nor Life, nor Angels, nor Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent nor things to come, nor height nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now our reconciliation to God by Jeſus Chriſt is a ground of joy and ſtrong conſolation
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102520:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt the terrours of Death, and troubles of Life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11. <hi>We joy in God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom we have now recieved an atonement.</hi> When we underſtand that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath made an atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for us, this may fill our hearts with joy, when death looks us in the face; when other men tremble at the thoughts of God, they that are reconciled to him may joy in God, both while they live and when they dye. In the next verſe, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of death entring into the world by ſin, and paſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men, for that all have ſinned. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. And in the 3d. and 4th. verſes he ſpeaks of the tribulations we are liable to in this life. <hi>We glory in Tribulations.</hi> Yet in all our tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and when we ſee death approaching and paſſing upon us, we may joy in God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by whom we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an atonement.</p>
                  <p>The knowledge of Gods love to our Souls may cauſe us to glory and rejoyce in the Lord in times of greateſt mortality, when Death is coming in at our Windows, and entred into our houſes, and cuts off both young and old, and there ſuch a multitude of dead corpſes that there are none to bury them. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.21, 22.24. <hi>Death is come up into our Windows, and is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into our Palaces, to cut off the children from without, and the young men from the ſtreets, ſpeak, thus ſaith the Lord, even the Carcaſſes of men ſhall fall as dung upon the open field, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102520:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>as the handful after the harveſt man, and none ſhall gather them — But let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he knoweth and underſtandeth me.</hi> We ſee here that a man may attain to glory in diſmal and dark days, in times of greateſt mortality, when death is cutting down multitudes in all places, our houſes, the ſtreets, the fields, and we may ſee in what a man may glory at ſuch a time, and that is in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods love; <hi>Let him glory in this that he knoweth and underſtandeth me that I am the Lord that exerciſeth loving kindneſs.</hi> It was a great comfort to <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he underſtood that <hi>Eſau</hi> was reconciled to him; while he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended his brother to be offended, and that he came to meet in diſpleaſure, he was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afraid and diſtreſſed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.7. But when he ſaw his Brother was pleaſed with him, that made him exceeding joyful, even as if he had a ſight of the face of God. <hi>Gen</hi> 33.10. <hi>I have ſeen thy face, as though I had ſeen the face of God, and thou waſt pleaſed with me.</hi> If reconciliation with an offended brother be ſuch a ground of comfort, what is reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with an offended God? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks highly of the favour of a King, that is like life to a dying man, and like the Rain to the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ground, very grateful and refreſhing. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.15. <hi>In the light of the Kings Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is Life, and his favour is as a Cloud of the latter Rain.</hi> If there be ſuch joy in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of an Earthly King, what joy is there in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102520:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the favour of the King of Kings. Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God affords ſtrong Conſolation againſt the Fears and Terrors of Death ſeveral ways.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Becauſe ſuch as are reconciled to God by the death of Chriſt ſhall aſſuredly be ſaved by Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>For if when we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son, much more being reconciled, we ſhall be ſaved by his Life.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Becauſe when God is reconciled to us, and his wrath turned away from us, we may truſt in him for Salvation, and all other good things, without being afraid of what death or men, or devils, or any creatures can do unto us; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.1, 2. <hi>O Lord I will praiſe thee, though thou waſt angry with me, thine anger is turned away, and thou haſt comforted me; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold God is my Salvation, I will trust, and not be afraid.</hi> When God is reconciled to us, we need not fear what man can do to us. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.7. <hi>The Lord is on my ſide, I will not fear. What can man do unto me?</hi> Man can kill the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and man can torture the body, but death can't hurt a man reconciled to God. VVhen God is reconciled we may triumph over all our enemies, not only over man, but over death and the grave, and the devils, and Hell it ſelf. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. <hi>What ſhall we then ſay to theſe things, if God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:102520:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p n="2">II. Jeſus Chriſt by his death hath obtained for all that are his, a free full, perpetual par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all their ſins, and this is a ground of ſtrong conſolation under the troubles of the world, and all the fears and terrors of death. The great end of Chriſts death was to expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate our ſins, and to obtain for us forgiveneſs of ſins. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Chriſt dyed for our ſins according to the Scriptures. Gal.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Who gave himſelf for our ſins.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>And ye know that he was manifeſt to take away our ſins Joh.</hi> 1.29. <hi>Behold the Lamb of God that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the ſin of the world. Heb.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Now once in the end of the world hath he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to put away ſin by the Sacrifice of himſelf.</hi> Now concerning this pardon which our Lord Jeſus hath obtained by his offering up himſelf a Sacrifice for us, let us obſerve theſe four things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is a full and general pardon of all and every one of our ſins; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi> All ſorts of ſins, ſins of Omiſſion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, ſins of Ignorance, and ſins againſt light, original and actual ſins are cleanſed away by the Blood of Chriſt, and every particular ſin, great and ſmall is cleanſed by the Blood of Chriſt. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity.</hi> He did not deſign our Redemption from ſome one ſin, or from many, but to redeem us from all iniquity by his giving himſelf to death for us.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102520:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>This was typified by the ſcape goat, over him <hi>Aaron</hi> laid his hands, and confeſſed all the ſins, and all the aggravations that were in the ſins of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the goat bore away all their iniquities into the land of forgetfulneſs. <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.21, 22. <hi>Aaron ſhall lay both his hands upon the head of the live goat, and confeſs over him all the Iniquities of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, and all their tranſgreſſions in all their ſins. —And the goat ſhall bear upon him all their iniquities into a Land not inhabited.</hi> This did ſignifie Gods laying all our ſins upon Chriſt. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. And Chriſt making ſatisfaction for them all, bearing them all away by his death. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Who his own ſelf, bare our ſins in his own body upon the tree.</hi> The diſcharge that Chriſt by his death hath obtained for us, is a full diſcharge. VVhatever ſin may be charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us, by the Law, by Conſcience, by Satan, who is our accuſer; by the juſtice of God, all is diſcharged, and quitted, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by the death of Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect. It is God that juſtifieth— It is Chriſt that dyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Out of reſpect to the Death of Chriſt, God will forgive us all our treſpaſſes, how many, or how great ſoever they have been. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Having forgiven you all treſpaſſes. Pſ.</hi> 103.3. <hi>Who forgiveth all thine iniquities. Pſ.</hi> 85.2. <hi>Thou haſt forgiven all the iniquities of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, thou haſt covered all our ſin.</hi> And that we
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102520:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>may be the more fully aſſured that the pardon which our Lord Jeſus hath obtained for us, is a full and general pardon of all offences, the Lord hath obliged himſelf by many promiſes for Chriſts ſake, to pardon all, and every one of our ſins. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.8. <hi>I will cleanſe them from all their Iniquity, whereby they have ſinned againſt me, and I will pardon all their Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whereby they have ſinned, and whereby they have tranſgreſſed againſt me. Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>From all your filthineſs, and all your Idols I will cleanſe you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Our Lord Jeſus hath obtained of God, that this general pardon ſhall be for ever, that all our ſins ſhould be forgiven for ever, and never be remembred againſt us to Eternity. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.12. <hi>I will be merciful to their unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and their ſins, and their Iniquities will I remember no more.</hi> And this is implyed in ſuch promiſes as theſe. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Thou wilt caſt all their ſins into the depths of the Sea:</hi> that is, as <hi>Druſius</hi> obſerv's, <hi>aeternâ oblivione dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit memoriam peccatorum noſtrorum.</hi> He will blot out the remembrance of our ſins for ever. Thoſe things that are caſt into the depths of the Sea, are wholly, and for ever, taken out of our ſight. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.12. <hi>As far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo far hath he removed our tranſgreſſious from us.</hi> That is, ſo far, as they ſhall never be laid to our charge any more. For the Eaſt and VVeſt are at that great diſtance, that they ſhall never come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102520:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.16. <hi>None of the ſins that he hath committed, ſhall be mentioned to him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Lord Jeſus hath obtained a general, and perpetual pardon of all offences, upon terms of free grace, without any reſpect to merit or worthineſs in us, that are partakers of it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Being juſtified freely by his Grace, through the Redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt. Eph.</hi> 1.7. <hi>In whom we have Redemption through his blood, the forgiveneſs of ſins, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the riches of his grace.</hi> It is from grace, free-graces, the riches of grace, that we have pardon of our Sins, through the blood of Chriſt. It is not for our ſakes, but for his own ſake, and his Sons ſake, that the Lord pardons our ſins. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>I, even I, am he that blotteth out thy Tranſgreſſions for mine own ſake, and will not remember t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y ſin Eph.</hi> 4.32. <hi>God, for Chriſts ſake, hath forgiven you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. This free, this everlaſting, this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pardon of all offences, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath purchaſed for all that are his; that is, for all that do, and all that ſhall believe in him, in all places, and all ages of the world. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.39. <hi>By him all that believe, are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from all things, from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of Moſes. Acts</hi> 10.43. <hi>To him gave all the Prophets witneſs, that through his name, whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this free, this everlaſting, this full and general pardon, which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102520:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath obtained for all that are his, by ſhedding his blood for them, is a ground of ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation under all the troubles of life, and all fears and terrours of death. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 3. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore juſtified by Faith—We glory in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations.</hi> Juſtified perſons, whoſe ſins are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted through the blood of Chriſt, may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not only when they are got out of their troubles, but when they are in the midſt of all their tribulations. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.24. <hi>The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſhall not ſay I am ſick, the people that dwell therein, ſhall be forgiven their iniquities.</hi> It is not ſaid the Inhabitant ſhall be without ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The greateſt of Gods favourites are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſickneſs, as well as other men. <hi>Daniel</hi> was a man, greatly beloved, yet he was ſick and faint many days. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.27. <hi>I Daniel fainted, and was ſick certain dayes.</hi> And it is ſaid of <hi>Lazarus, John</hi> 11.3. <hi>Lord, he, whom thou loveſt, is ſick.</hi> Juſtified perſons are oft times ſick, as well as other men, but the pardon of ſin, doth ſo ſweeten their affliction, that they ſhall not ſay I am ſick; that is, they ſhall not ſay by way of complaint, and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Sin unpardoned, makes afflictions like gall and wormwood, that is, exceeding bitter. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.5, 15, 42. <hi>He bath compaſſed me with gall — He hath filled me with bitterneſs, he hath made me drunken with worm wood — We have tranſgreſſed and rebelled, and thou haſt not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned</hi> But pardon of ſin doth ſo ſweeten the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt afflictions, that it takes away all cauſes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102520:20"/>of complaint under the rod of God. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant ſhall not ſay I am ſick, and why is it, becauſe there is no ſickneſs? No, but becauſe the people that dwell therein ſhall be forgiven their iniquitie. VVhen a man is taken ſick, and his ſickneſs for ought he knoweth, may be his death ſickneſs; when he is ſo ſick, that he can't go, or ſtand, or ſet up, but is confined to his Bed: if his ſins be forgiven him, he may be of good cheer. <hi>Math.</hi> 9.2. <hi>Son be of good cheer, thy ſins be forgiven thee.</hi> Here is a ſick man, his ſickneſs was very uncomfortable, he was ſick of the Palſie, he was brought very low, he kept his Bed, there was no way for his recovery but a miracle; yet before Chriſt gave him any intimation of his purpoſe to heal him, he bid him be of good cheer, and why! becauſe his ſins were forgiven him.</p>
                  <p>This pardon of all our ſins, which is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for us by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, may comfort us againſt all the fears and terrours of Death, on ſeveral accounts.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) VVhen our ſins are pardoned, the ſting of Death is taken away. <hi>For the ſting of Death is ſin.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. And when Sin is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, Death hath loſt its ſting, and when the ſting of Death is taken away, we need not be afraid of Death, it can do us no harm.</item>
                     <item>(2.) VVhen our ſins are pardoned, we may be aſſured our Souls ſhall be ſaved; for God glorifieth all whom he juſtifieth. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified. Tit.</hi> 3.7.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102520:21"/>
                        <hi>That being juſtified by his grace, we ſhould be made Heirs, according to the hope of eternal life.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Jeſus Chriſt, by his death and ſufferings, hath obtained for all that are his, freedom from eternal condemnation, and this is a ground of ſtrong conſolation under all the troubles of this life, and againſt the fears and terrours of Death. There is not any one perſon that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to Chriſt, that hath an intereſt in Chriſt, that ſhall come into condemnation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> That our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath redeemed all that are his from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal condemnation, is evident ſeveral wayes.
<list>
                           <item>1. Becauſe Chriſt dyed for us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. Who ſhall condemn? It is Chriſt <hi>that dyed.</hi> The Death of Chriſt is our ſecurity from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death. He laid down his life on purpoſe to ranſome us from Eternal condemnation. <hi>Math.</hi> 20.28. <hi>The Son of man came to give his life a ranſome for many;</hi> out of reſpect to, and for the ſake of this ranſome, God will deliver all that are Chriſts, from going down into the bottomleſs pit. <hi>Job</hi> 33.24. <hi>Deliver him from going down into the pit, for I have found a ranſom.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. The ground and cauſe of our Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is taken away by the Death of Chriſt, which is ſin. For God condemneth no man but for ſin; and therefore Chriſt having by his Death taken away our ſins, hath taken away condemnation from us.</item>
                           <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102520:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                           <item>3. God out of reſpect to the death and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt hath promiſed, that none that believe in Chriſt ſhall come into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16, 18. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son that whoſoever believeth on him ſhould not periſh, but ſhould have everlaſting life — He that believeth on him is not condemned. Job.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, he that heareth my word, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on him that ſent me hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from Death unto Life.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. The Keys of Hell are in the hands of Jeſus Chriſt, he hath power to caſt into Hell, and to keep out of Hell whom he pleaſeth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.18. <hi>I am he that liveth and was dead, and behold I am alive for evermore, Amen, and have the Keys of Hell and of Death</hi> And if the Keys of Hell be in the hands of Chriſt, then all they that are Chriſts are upon ſure grounds, that they ſhall not come into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, for he will not in any wife caſt any of his Members into eternal torments. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. <hi>Him that cometh unto me I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And ſeeing all they that are Chriſts are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from eternal condemnation, this may comfort them under all the troubles of this world, and againſt the fears and terrors of Death. It may ſcatter and diſpel all our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and fill our hearts with joy and gladneſs when we underſtand and believe that we are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102520:22"/>ranſomed and delivered from eternal torments. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. <hi>The ranſomed of the Lord ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and come to</hi> Zion <hi>with Songs, and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy upon their heads, they ſhall obtain joy and gladneſs, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away.</hi> This hath relation to the deliverance of the <hi>Jews</hi> out of the Babylonian Captivity, which was a type of our deliverance from eternal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; when God brought them out of their captivity, they were filled with joy and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1, 2. <hi>When the Lord turned again the captivity of</hi> Zion, <hi>Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging.</hi> Now if there were ſuch joy and ſinging by the ranſomed of the Lord, that were delivered from <hi>Babylon,</hi> what joy and gladneſs may ariſe to the ranſomed of the Lord from their deliverance from Hell torments? Hell is a worſe place than <hi>Babylon,</hi> the captivity of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> was but for 70 years, but Hell torments are for Eternity. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from Hell as an unexpreſſible Mercy. and that he would praiſe God with all his heart, and glorifie him for evermore, for ſuch a great mercy. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.12, 13. <hi>I will praiſe thee O Lord my God with all my heart, and I will glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy name for evermore, for great is thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy toward me, and thou haſt delivered my Soul from the lowest Hell.</hi> And this his deliverance from the loweſt Hell was a comfort to him, when the proud roſe up againſt him, and the aſſemblies of violent men ſought after his Soul.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102520:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 14.17. When we know and believe that we are freed from condemnation by the death of Chriſt, this may cauſe us to triumph over death, when we are killed all the day long, and counted as Sheep for the ſlaughter. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34, 36, 37. <hi>Who ſhall condemn? It is Chriſt that dyed — For thy ſake we are killed all the day long, we are accounted as Sheep for the ſlaughter, Nay in all theſe things we are more then Conquerors through him that loved us.</hi> When we are freed from condemnation, we may triumph over Death, though we walk in danger of Death all the day long, more than Conquerours triumph over their conquered enemies.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. They that are Chriſts have a ſure and undoubted right to eternal life, and that ſure hope which they have of eternal life is a ground of ſtrong conſolation under all the troubles of this life, and againſt the fears and terrours of Death. They that are Chriſts have a ſure and undoubted right to Eternal Life 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.12. <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life.</hi> It is not ſaid, he ſhall have Life, but he hath Life, that is, he may be as ſure of it, as if he had it already. He hath an undoubted right, an unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Title to eternal life. He hath it in the purpoſe and decree of God, he hath it in the promiſe of God; And that by life here, is meant eternal life is evident from the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words; they that have Chriſt dwelling in their hearts by Faith, have a ſure ground and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102520:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>foundation for their hope of eternal glory. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of Glory.</hi> That all that are Chriſts have an undoubted right to, and ſure grounds to hope for eternal Life; may be demonſtrated ſeveral wayes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt dyed on purpoſe that he might purchaſe and procure eternal life for all that ſhould believe on him. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>As</hi> Moſes <hi>liſted up the Serpent in the Wilderneſs, ſo muſt the Son of man be lifted up, that whoſoever believeth on him ſhould not periſh, but have eternal life.</hi> By the lifting up of the Son of man is meant his ſuffering death upon the Croſs. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32, 33. And this death he ſuffered that he might purchaſe eternal life for all that ſhould believe on him. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.9, 10. <hi>God hath not appointed us unto wrath, but to obtain Salvation by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who died for us, that whether we wake or ſleep, we ſhould live together with him.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt interceedeth with his Father on the behalf of all thoſe that are given to him, that they may be with him where he is, that is, in the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17 24. <hi>Father I will, that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo whom thou hast given me be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory, which thou haſt given me.</hi> And what Chriſt asked of his Father ſhall aſſuredly be granted. <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.42. <hi>I know that thou heareſt me always.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. God for Chriſts ſake hath promiſed eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life to all that are Chriſts, that is, to all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102520:23"/>perſons that do or ſhall believe on Chriſt to the end of the World. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>For God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son this whoſoever believeth on him ſhould not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh but have everlasting life.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.25. <hi>And this is the promiſe, that he hath promiſed us eternal life.</hi> And the promiſe of God is a ſure ground to hope for eternal life. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. <hi>In hope of eternal life, which God that cannot lie promiſed before the World began.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath power over all fleſh given to him by the Father, that he may give eternal life to all that are given to him by the Father. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2. <hi>As thou hast given him power over all fleſh, that he ſhould give eternal life, to as many as thou haſt given him.</hi> And therefore they that are Chriſts may be aſſured that they ſhall have eternal life, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt hath power to give eternal life to whom he will, and this power over all fleſh was given him purpoſely that he might give eternal life to all that were given him by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                     <item>5. God hath given us this record concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son, that eternal life is in his Son, and that eternal life is his free gift, and that he will give it to all that have his Son, and if we do not believe this record that God hath given of his Son we ſhould make God a Liar. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.10, 11, 12. <hi>He that believeth not God hath made him a Liar, becauſe he believeth not the record that God gave of his Son. And this is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102520:24"/>the record that God hath given us eternal life, and this life is in his Son, he that hath the Son hath Life.</hi> Eternal Life is in Chriſt, and therefore if we believe the record that God hath given of his Son, namely that God hath given us eternal life, and that this life is in his Son, we muſt then conclude it as a certain truth, that he that hath the Son, hath Life.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Now ſeeing ſuch as have an intereſt in Chriſt, have ſure grounds to hope for eternal life, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth hence that they have good grounds of ſtrong conſolation under all the troubles of this life, and alſo againſt the fears and terrors of Death For hope of eternal life will help us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce greatly in the midſt of all our troubles. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2, 3 <hi>VVe rejoyce in hope of the glory of God, and not only ſo, but we glory in tribulations.</hi> When we have good hope of the glory of God, that is, of enjoying the Kingdom of Heaven, which is a moſt glorious Kingdom, we may rejoyce and glory in the midſt of our greateſt tribulations. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4, 6. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his abundant mercy hath begotten us again to a lively hope, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, to an inheritance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible and vndefiled, that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven for you: wherein ye greatly rejoyce, though now for a ſeaſon if need be, ye are in hearineſs through manifold temptations.</hi> Here is joy, great joy in the midſt of manifold temptations that did cauſe heavineſs, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102520:24"/>whence did this joy proceed? from a lively hope of an heavenly inheritance. <hi>VVherein ye greatly rejoyce</hi> — That is, in which hope, or in hope of which inheritance. So <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. <hi>Ye took joyfully the ſpoyling of your goods, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your ſelves that ye have in Heaven a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more enduring ſubſtance.</hi> The ſpoyling of our goods for which we have laboured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years is wont to cauſe ſorrow and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.19. <hi>A voice of wailing is heard out of</hi> Zion, <hi>how are we ſpoyled!</hi> yet the hope of a reward in Heaven will help us to take the ſpoiling of our goods joyfully.</p>
                  <p>The hope of eternal life will take away the fears and terrors of Death, when a man hath good hope of his Salvation, it will be no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, no terror to ſuch a man to dye, but he may dye in peace. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.29, 30. <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen thy Salvation.</hi> The hope of eternal life will ſo far take off the fear and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of death, that it will make us deſire and long for our diſſolution, that we may be with Chriſt in Heaven. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to depart and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>VVe know that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands eternal in the heavens. For in this we groan earneſtly, deſiring to be cloathed upon with our houſe which is from Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">V. They that are Chriſts ſhall have the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102520:25"/>Lords preſence with them, under the troubles which they meet with while they live, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when they come to die. Our ſins made a ſeparation between God and our Souls. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2. But the ſufferings of Chriſt have made up this breach. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>For Chriſt alſo ſuffered once for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, that we might be brought unto God.</hi> One of the names given to Chriſt was <hi>Emmanuel, which being interpreted is God with us. Math.</hi> 1.23. Whereas by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> God was againſt us, and was ſeparated from us, through Chriſt he is reconciled to us, and is become with us, a God that will afford us his preſence; That ſuch as are Chriſts ſhall have the preſence of God and Chriſt with them under all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, yea at all times both while they live and when they dye. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>He hath ſaid I will never leave thee nor forſake thee.</hi> And what he hath ſaid he will ſurely perform it. If he will never leave nor forſake us, then at no time of life, nor at the hour of death. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Lo I am with you always to the end of the world.</hi> Here is a note of attention ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this promiſe, that the Members of Chriſt may take notice of it for their comfort and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement. <hi>Lo I am with you</hi> — I that have all power in Heaven and in Earth given to me, I am with you, how long? always to the end of the world, not only with his Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Diſciples that lived in thoſe days, but with all his Miniſters and Members to the end
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102520:25"/>of the world, and at all times. And more eſpecially in times of trouble, the Lord hath promiſed his preſence to ſuch as belong to Chriſt. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.15. <hi>He ſhall call upon me, and I will anſwer him, I will be with him in trouble. Iſa.</hi> 43.1, 2. <hi>Fear not, For I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy name, thou art mine. When thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee, and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee, when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhall not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the preſence of God going along with us, will comfort us, living and dying; it will be our refreſhment under all manner of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.14. <hi>My preſence ſhall go with thee, and I will give thee rest. Moſes</hi> was forty years in the Wilderneſs with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who were a froward people, and both the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of the place in which he walked, and the difficulties of the people among whom he walked, created him much vexation and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but under his troubles he found eaſe and comfort from the preſence of God, going with him. A man that hath the Almighty, All-ſufficient God with him, need not fear any thing. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Fear thou not, for I am with thee; be thou not diſmayed, for I am thy God.</hi> He need not fear any kind of Death, or any kind of troubles; he need not fear Men or Devils: for God can do more for us, then all Creatures can do againſt us. This was <hi>Davids</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:102520:26"/>conſolation againſt the fear of Death, that he had God with him, and did ſo raiſe his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, that he feared no evil, when he was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Yea, though I walk through the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of the ſhadow of Death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> It is true may ſome ſay, If God were with us, this would raiſe our Faith, diſpel our fears, put joy and gladneſs into our hearts, under all our troubles, living and dying; but we can't find God is with us. Yea, many that have an intereſt in Chriſt, find God ſtanding afar off, and hideing himſelf in time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: as we ſee, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord is alway's ready and truly, though not always ſenſibly preſent with them. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 125.2. <hi>As the Mountains are round about Jeruſalem, ſo the Lord is round about his people, from henceforth, even for ever.</hi> The Lord is for ever with, and round about his people; although ſometimes their eyes are held, and they perceive it not. And then their Faith is weak, ſo that judging by Sence, rather than by Faith, they think God hath forſaken them, when as he is graciouſly with them, and they know it not. What <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of the place where he lodged, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.16. <hi>Surely the Lord was in this place, and I knew it not.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of ſome perſons, <hi>Surely the Lord is with them, and they know it not.</hi> Now the Lord is alwayes with his people theſe two
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102520:26"/>wayes, even when they are ready to ſay that he hath forſaken them.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. He is preſent with them in reſpect of his love and favour. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>My kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee. Pſ.</hi> 89.33. <hi>Nevertheleſs my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take away from him. Joh.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Jeſus having loved his own, loved them to the end.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Lord is alwayes preſent with his people by inward ſupports, and ſecret uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.27. <hi>The eternal God is thy refuge, and underneath are the everlaſting armes — Iſa.</hi> 41.10. <hi>Fear thou not, for I am with thee — I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſs. Pſ.</hi> 73.23. <hi>Nevertheleſs I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually with thee, thou haſt holden me by my right hand.</hi> Though <hi>David</hi> was ready to ſay in his haſt, that he was caſt out of Gods ſight, yet he found upon recollecting himſelf, that he was continually with God, and upheld by him.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="6">6. Intereſt in Chriſt is a ground of ſtrong conſolation under all ſorts of troubles, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo againſt the terrours of Death, becauſe they that are Chriſts are in covenant with God, and are heirs of all the promiſes. They are in Covenant with God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. <hi>I ſware unto thee, and entred into a Covenant with thee, ſaith the Lord God, and thou becameſt mine.</hi> They are Heirs of all the promiſes. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>And if you be Chriſts, then are ye Abrahams ſeed, and heirs according to the promiſe.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:102520:27"/>1.20. <hi>For all the promiſes of God in him are yea, and in him Amen to the glory of God by us.</hi> If all the promiſes of God be upon, and Amen in Chriſt, then when Chriſt is ours, all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God are ours. And this is a ground of ſtrong conſolation under all manner of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to be in covenant with God, and to have an intereſt in all the promiſes of God. For the Scripture is full of great and precious promiſes, promiſes of all good things pertaining to this life, and the life which is to come; and to have an intereſt in all theſe promiſes, is a matter of unſpeakable joy. By acquaintance with the covenant and promiſe of God, our Souls may dwell at eaſe, whatever troubles come upon our outward man. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.13, 14. <hi>His Soul ſhall dwell at eaſe — and he will ſhew them his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> The Pſalmiſt ſpeaking of a man that feareth God, ſaith, <hi>his Soul ſhall dwell at eaſe</hi>—and then ſheweth how this is brought to paſs, and that is, by acquaintance with the Covenant, <hi>He will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi> The dwelling of the Soul at eaſe, implyeth the abundance and continuance of inward and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comforts, which are enjoyed by our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the Covenant, The promiſes are ſweet Cordials, which refreſh the Soul in times of greateſt diſtreſs. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 60.6. <hi>God hath ſpoken in his holineſs, I will rejoyce.</hi> In the three firſt verſes, there are ſad complaints of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous afflictions, <hi>O God thou haſt caſt us off, thou haſt ſcattered us, thou haſt been diſpleaſed—Thou
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102520:27"/>haſt made the Earth tremble, thou haſt broken it—Thou haſt ſhewed thy people hard things, thou hast made us to drink the wine of aſtoniſhment.</hi> Now what will comfort a man at ſuch a time as this? What will make a man rejoyce un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch amazing providences, when God ſeems to caſt off, and be diſpleaſed? when God ſcatters his people, ſhewes them hard things, makes them drink the Wine of aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, when the very Earth trembles at Gods judgments? The promiſes of God will comfort in ſuch a dark day as this is, <hi>God hath ſpoken in his holineſs, I will rejoyce.</hi> When <hi>David</hi> was in a perſecuted condition, and they that perſecuted him, were no mean men, but great Perſons, Princes, <hi>Saul,</hi> and his Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, he had exceeding great joy in the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.161, 162. <hi>Princes have perſecuted me without a cauſe—I rejoyce at thy word as one that findeth great ſpoil.</hi> When <hi>David</hi> was in a dying condition, he found ſtrong conſolation from his intereſt in Gods covenant. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.1, 5. <hi>Now theſe be the laſt words of David—Although my houſe be not ſo with God, yet he hath made with me an Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, ordered in all things, and ſure: for this is all my deſire, and all my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, although he make it not to grow.</hi> See what was <hi>Davids</hi> comfort, when he was ſpeaking his laſt words, it was his intereſt in the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant. <hi>He hath made with me an Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> and the aſſurance he had
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102520:28"/>of his Salvation by virtue of this Covenant. <hi>This is all my Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Intereſt in Chriſt is a ground of ſtrong conſolation under all ſorts of troubles, and againſt the terrours of Death; becauſe when Chriſt is ours, all his ſaving benefits are ours. As <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid to <hi>Benhadad,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.4. <hi>I am thine, and all that I have.</hi> So may I ſay, If Chriſt be thine, all <hi>that Chriſt hath is thine.</hi> Hence ſuch as are intereſted in Chriſt, are ſaid to be <hi>joynt heirs with Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.17. When Chriſt is ours, all things are ours, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and things to come, life and death, this world, and the world to come; adverſitie and proſperitie, all things are ours, ordained and deſigned for our good. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22, 23. <hi>All things are yours, whether Paul or Apollo, or Cephas, or the world, or life or death, or things preſent, or things to come, all are yours, and ye are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods.</hi> And if this will not comfort us to hear that life and death, things preſent, and things to come, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, and all things are ours, what elſe will. VVhen Chriſt is ours, his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is ours. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. His blood, and all that he hath purchaſed with his blood, all his merits are ours, and his interceſſion is ours. God is our Father, the Spirit is our comforter, Heaven is our Inheritance, yea, all good things are ours.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102520:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> How is this true, that they are Chriſts, have all things, when as many that are Chriſts, are ful of wants; they want Riches, Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in great ſtraits, and have ſuffered the loſs of all things for Chriſt; and can theſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent together, that a man ſhould have all things, and yet want many things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. They that are Chriſts, have all things vertually in that contentment and ſatisfaction which they have in Chriſt, and from Chriſt. They are, or may be as well contented, as if they had all the world. Thus it was with the Apoſtle in his wants and ſtraits, when he was as poor to outward appearance, as a man that hath nothing; he was as well contented, as if he had poſſeſſed the whole world. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> A man that hath a contented mind, is as well ſatisfied, as if he had all the world. <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.11. Take I pray thee my bleſſing, that is brought unto thee, becauſe God hath dealt graciouſly with me, and I have enough. The Hebrew is <hi>li chol,</hi> I have all things. Hence note that they have enough, that have contented and ſatisfied minds, they have all things.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They that are Chriſts, have all things in the providential care of God, though they be poor, and in ſtraits, and have ſuffered the loſs
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102520:29"/>of all things, the providence of God takes care of them to ſupply them with all things that are needful, with all things that are good for them. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Caſting all your care upon him, for he careth for you.</hi> The providence of God taketh ſuch care for us in all things, that we need not trouble our ſelves with anxious thoughts, or cares about any thing, but may caſt all our care upon the Lord. The Providence of God doth, and will take care of us, to ſupply us with all needful things, and all things that are good for us. <hi>Phil</hi> 4.19. <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all your need, according to his riches in glory, by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. They have all things in the Covenant and Promiſe of God. For in the Covenant there are all things promiſed, that they do, or can deſire. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. <hi>He hath made with me an Everlaſting Covenant, and this is all my Salvation, and all my deſire.</hi> VVe can't deſire more then Grace and Glory, and all good things, now theſe are all promiſed to us. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84.11. <hi>The Lord God is a Sun and a Shield, the Lord will give grace and glory, and no good thing will he withhold from them that walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly.</hi> And what things are ours by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, are ours by a better, and a more ſure tenure, then what is ours by actual poſſeſſion without a promiſe, becauſe what we have in our poſſeſſion, may be loſt, may be taken from us, but the promiſes no creature can take from us.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:102520:29"/>
                  <p n="4">4. They have all things eminently and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendently in God and Chriſt, in having God for their portion, and Chriſt for their Saviour. What <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith of mony. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Mony anſwereth all things.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid as truly of God and Chriſt; God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth all things, and Chriſt anſwereth all things. When we enjoy God who is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all good, in the enjoyment of him, for our God, we do inherit all things. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. <hi>He that overcometh ſhall inherit all things, and I will be his God, and he ſhall be my Son.</hi> They have all things in Chriſt their head, what the head hath, the head hath it for the good of the Members. Now Chriſt our head hath all things for the good of his church. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22. <hi>And gave him to be the head over all things in the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. They have the good of all things, though not the actual poſſeſſion of all things. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>VVe know that all things work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good to them, that love God.</hi> Yea their very wants are for their good; for they put them upon living by Faith, and ſtir up in them a Spirit of Prayer, and keep them hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. They are heirs of all things, though they are not come to the full enjoyment of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; for they are joynt heirs with Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>If children then heirs, heirs of God,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102520:30"/>and joynt heirs with Chriſt.</hi> And Chriſt is heir of all things. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken to us by his Son, whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed heir of all things.</hi> The heir while a child is Lord of all, though he hath not the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual poſſeſſion of his inheritance. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1. So it is with us, we are heirs of all things by virtue of our Union with Chriſt, though we have not the actual poſſeſſion of our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Intereſt in Chriſt is a ground of ſtrong conſolation, under all troubles of life and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of death, becauſe all that are Chriſts are bleſſed in and by Chriſt, and are ſo bleſſed as no troubles, nor death it ſelf can make them miſerable, but after their Union with Chriſt, they are bleſſed, and ſhall continue bleſſed for ever. I ſhall open the bleſſedneſs of ſuch as are Chriſts in theſe particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) All that are Chriſts, are in a moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and happy condition. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him. Gal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>In thee ſhall all Nations be bleſſed.</hi> That is, in thy ſeed that ſhall proceed out of thy loins, that is, the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> as appears from <hi>Act.</hi> 3.25, 26. By all Nations being bleſſed in Chriſt, we are to underſtand all perſons in all Nations that believe on Chriſt, as the following words ſhew. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>So then they which be of faith are bleſſed with faithful</hi> Abraham; what <hi>Laban</hi> ſaid concerning <hi>Jacob. Gen.</hi> 30.27. <hi>I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102520:30"/>have learned by experience, that the Lord hath bleſſed me for thy ſake.</hi> That may they that are Chriſts ſay concerning Chriſt, I have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by experience that the Lord hath bleſſed me for Chriſts ſake.</item>
                     <item>(2.) They that are Chriſts are bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſſings in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Eph</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who hath bleſſed us with all ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly places in Chriſt.</hi> Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al bleſſings are the beſt bleſſings, now God hath not only bleſſed us with ſome, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but with all ſpiritual bleſſings, and that not only all ſpiritual bleſſings which are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in this life, but with all ſpiritual bleſſings which are reſerved for us in heavenly places. And we are bleſſed with all theſe ſpiritual bleſſings both pertaining to this life, and to be enjoyed in heavenly places in the life to come, in Chriſt Jeſus. Which is better than if we had them in our own hands. For <hi>Adam</hi> had all bleſſings in his own hands, and loſt them, but what is put into the hands of Chriſt he will keep ſafe for ever.</item>
                     <item>(3.) That bleſſedneſs which we have in and by Jeſus Chriſt, is eternal bleſledneſs. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that bleſſedneſs which they that are Chriſts have in this life, all the bleſſings of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven are prepared for them, and ſhall be given to them for their inheritance. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom prepared for you from the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102520:31"/>foundation of the world.</hi> His bleſſing is eternal life. God hath bleſſed us in Chriſt with the higheſt bleſſings he had to give, and we were capable to recieve, and that for ever. For through Chriſt he hath given himſelf unto us, to be our God. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.28. <hi>I will be your God.</hi> And he hath promiſed to give us his Kingdom. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Fear not little flock, for it is your Fathers good pleaſure to give you the Kingdom.</hi> And what greater bleſſings hath God to give than himſelf and his Kingdom. And therefore what is ſaid of <hi>David? Pſal.</hi> 21.6. <hi>Thou haſt made him moſt bleſſed for ever.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of all that are Chriſts, God hath not only made them bleſſed, but hath made them moſt bleſſed for ever; for they that come to Chriſt upon the call of the Goſpel are made partakers of the ſure mercies of <hi>David. Iſa.</hi> 53.3.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="4">4. It is the immutable purpoſe and unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble promiſe of God to make all the Members of Chriſt moſt bleſſed for ever, and he hath confirmed the immutability of his counſel and promiſe with his oath: which may give ſtrong conſolation to all that in the ſenſe of their loſt and undone condition have fled for refuge to Jeſus Chriſt, that by and in him they may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Life and Salvation. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13, 14, 17.18. This portion of Scripture ſetting forth the great aſſurance which God hath given all that believe in Chriſt, that he will make them bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and happy for ever, which is a foundation
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102520:31"/>of ſtrong conſolation, I ſhall obſerve ſeveral things out of it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. God made a promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> that in bleſſing he would bleſs him, that is, that he would give him all things requiſite to true bleſſedneſs, that he would make him moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and bleſſed for ever, that he would never leave off bleſſing him, but would bleſs him for ever. This includes the promiſe of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, for no man is a bleſſed man, but he that ſhall have eternal life, all others are under Gods curſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34, 41. The bleſſings of Heaven are the main part of our bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. God confirmed this promiſe of giving <hi>Abraham</hi> all things requiſite to true bleſſedneſs, with the greateſt oath that he could ſwear. For, <hi>becauſe he could ſwear by no greater, he ſware by himſelf, ſaying, ſurely bleſſing I will bleſs thee. ſurely,</hi> that is, <hi>ſurely as I live,</hi> as ſure as I am God, I will bleſs thee, and make thee bleſſed for ever.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This promiſe and this oath were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but intended for the ſtrengthning of the Faith, and the conſolation of all the heirs of promiſe to the end of the world. <hi>Wherein,</hi> that is <hi>in which promiſe, God willing to ſhew to the heirs of promiſe</hi> — 'Tis not ſaid to ſhew to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but to ſhew to the heirs of promiſe, confirmed it with an oath, ſo that the promiſe and oath of God are intended for all the heirs of promiſe. That
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102520:32"/>we might have a ſtrong conſolation. 'Tis not ſaid <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo that the oath and promiſe of God is as much for our comfort as <hi>Abrahams.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Gods oath added to his promiſe ſheweth that his counſel and decree for bleſſing <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and all the heirs of promiſe is immutable, he will not alter his purpoſe or promiſe of bleſſing any of the heirs of promiſe.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. God is abundantly willing that the heirs of promiſe ſhould know the immutability of his counſel of giving them all things requiſite to true bleſſedneſs.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Such as have fled to Chriſt for refuge, to be ſaved from wrath to come, and to give them eternal life may have ſtrong conſolation. <hi>That we might have a ſtrong conſolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope ſet before us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By fleeing for refuge we may underſtand fleeing to Chriſt, that we may eſcape from wrath to come, and may obtain eternal life and Salvation. The Cities of refuge under the law, whether the Man-ſlayer was to flee that he might be preſerved from the avenger of Blood, did typifie Chriſt to whom we are to flee for refuge that we may eſcape the wrath and vengeance of God, which is due to us for our ſins. Eternal Life is the hope which is ſet before us to be laid hold upon. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Looking for that bleſſed hope</hi> — That is for eternal life. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. <hi>In hope of eternal life</hi> — This hope is ſet before us in the Goſpel.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102520:32"/>
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. <hi>For the hope which is laid up for you in Heaven, whereof ye heard before in the word of the Truth of the Goſpel.</hi> And therefore it is called the hope of the Goſpel <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>And be not moved away from the hope of the Goſpel.</hi> This is the hope we are to lay hold upon. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Lay hold upon Eternal Life.</hi> So that our fleeing for refuge to lay hold on the hope ſet before us, is this, our fleeing unto Jeſus Chriſt that we may eſcape that wrath which is due to us for our ſins, and that we may in him and through him obtain Eternal Life and Salvation.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. They that have thus fled for refuge, have the promiſe and oath of God, which are two immutable things, to aſſure them that God in bleſſing will bleſs them. For the oath and promiſe is to them as well as unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> and what doth this imply, <hi>Surely bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing I will bleſs thee.</hi> A. Surely I will pardon all thy ſins. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.7, 8. And ſurely I will give thee eternal life. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. and 5.3. And ſurely I will pour out my Spirit upon thee. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. And ſurely I will turn thee from thine iniquities. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.26. And ſurely I will give thee all good things. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 21.3. And ſurely I will make thee a bleſſed man for ever. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.27.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Theſe two immutable things, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and the oath of God, as ſure as he liveth to bleſs for ever all that flee to Chriſt for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, this may give them ſtrong conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102520:33"/>yea this may give them ſuch ſtrong conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation as no troubles, nothing whatever ſhall make void their comfort; which is the next head I am to ſpeak to.</p>
                  <p n="5">(5.) The bleſſed eſtate and condition of ſuch as have an intereſt in Chriſt is made ſo ſure, and ſo firmly ſetled upon them, that no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this life, nor Death it ſelf can make void their bleſſedneſs. They are and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue bleſſed under all their afflictions and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as well as in their greateſt proſperity. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chaſtneth O Lord, and teacheſt out of thy Law. Jam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth Temptation, for when he is tryed, he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieve the Crown of Life which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him.</hi> They are and continue bleſſed, when they dye as well as while they live. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord.</hi> Death is ſo far from making void the bleſſedneſs of thoſe that are Chriſts, that it puts them into the actual poſſeſſion of the Bleſſings of Heaven, which is far greater bleſſedneſs then they enjoyed, whilſt they were in this world.</p>
                  <p>Now the favour which God hath ſhewn to thoſe that are Chriſts in beſtowing all this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs upon them, and in making them moſt bleſſed for ever, is a ground of exceeding great joy. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.6. <hi>Thou haſt made him moſt bleſſed for ever, thou haſt made him exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glad with thy countenance.</hi> This bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102520:33"/>which is confirmed to them that are Chriſts by two immutable things, the oath and the promiſe of God is a ground of ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all eſtates and conditions, of ſuch ſtrong Conſolation as cannot be made void by any troubles or by death it ſelf, as hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed from <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13, 14, 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. More grounds of conſolation againſt the troubles of the world, to ſuch as have an intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Seeing the way to Heaven lyeth through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tribulations, and experience ſheweth it is an hard matter for Chriſtians to bear up chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully under the manifold troubles they meet with in this world, I ſhall add ſome more grounds of comfort for ſuch as have an intereſt in Chriſt, againſt all the troubles they are lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to in this world.</p>
                  <p>§. The World is conquered by Chriſt. what comfort ariſeth hence.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is a great comfort to a Chriſtian un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the troubles of the world, to conſider that Chriſt hath overcome the World. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.32. <hi>In the world ye ſhall have tribulation, but be of good chear, I have overcome the world.</hi> By the world which Chriſt hath overcome we may underſtand all things that are in the world which hinder the peace, Conſolation and Salvation of the Members of Chriſt, as the Prince of the World, which is a Title given to Satan,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102520:34"/>the Rulers of the world, the men of the world, the troubles of the world, the temptations of the world, the corruptions that are in the world through Luſt. All that is in the world, which is contrary to us, Chriſt hath overcome for us. Now Chriſts overcoming the world is a ground of comfort againſt the troubles of the world on ſeveral accounts, as.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Jeſus Chriſt having overcome the world, the whole world with all things in the world, is now at his diſpoſal. The Prince of the world, and all the powers of the world, and all the men of the world can do nothing in the world but by the permiſſion of Chriſt. He is Prince of the Kings of the earth, and governs and over-rules all their counſels and deſigns. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Prince of the Kings of the Earth.</hi> The men of the world can do nothing againſt any of the Members of Chriſt, though they be great men, though Rulers, but what he gives them power to do. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.11. <hi>Thou couldſt have no power at all againſt me, except it were given thee from above.</hi> What Chriſt ſaith here of himſelf concerning <hi>Pilate,</hi> is true of all his Members, concerning all the Rulers of the world, they can have no power at all againſt any of the Members of Chriſt, except it be given them from above, and this is a great quieting to the hearts of the People of God againſt the men and troubles of the world.</item>
                     <item>2. Jeſus Chriſt who overcame the World
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102520:34"/>is <hi>the Captain of our Salvation. Heb.</hi> 2.10. And he did not only overcome the world for himſelf, but for us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Who gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for our ſins, that he might deliver us from this preſent evil world, according to the will of God and our Father.</hi> By his Conqueſt he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained our deliverance from this preſent evil world. We may expect while we are in the world ſharp Conflicts with the troubles of the world. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Ye endured a great ſight of Afflictions.</hi> But this is our comfort, we have to do with a Conquered Enemy, an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that may oppoſe us, but ſhall not hurt us. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Behold I give unto you power to tread on Serpents and Scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing ſhall by any means hurt you.</hi> Serpents are an embleme of ſubtle enemies. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Now the Serpent was more ſubtle than any Beast of the Field. Mat.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Be wiſe as Serpents.</hi> And of cruel enemies that ſeek our deſtruction. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.9. <hi>They were deſtroyed of Serpents.</hi> The worſt of men are compared to Scorpions. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.6. <hi>And thou Son of man be not afraid of them, neither be afraid of their words, though Briars and Thorns be with thee, and thou doſt dwell among Scorpions.</hi> Scorpions here ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies wicked men which ſpoke big words againſt the Prophet. Now by the help of Chriſt we ſhall tread on thoſe enemies that are like Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents and Scorpions, and all the power of the enemy, ſo far as nothing ſhall by any means
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102520:35"/>hurt us. And there are three negatives in the Greek, which is the more remarkable to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us of the truth of what is ſpoken.</item>
                     <item>3. Jeſus Chriſt who hath overcome the World, will enable us through Faith in him to overcome the world our ſelves. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4.5. <hi>Whatſoever is born of God overcometh the World, and this is the Victory that overcometh the world, even our Faith. Who is he that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the world, but he that believeth that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the Son of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. By Chriſt; overcoming the world, the world is become ours, the troubles of the world which would of themſelves hinder our Salvation, ſhall be made through the Conqueſt of Chriſt to further our Salvation. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.19. <hi>I know that this ſhall turn to my Salvation.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks of his Bonds, and of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions ſome evil minded men thought to add to his Bonds; <hi>ver</hi> 13.16. And he knew that his afflictions ſhould be ſo far from hindring, that it ſhould be a furtherance of his Salvation. See alſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.6. <hi>VVhether we be afflicted it is for your Conſolation and Salvation, which is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual in enduring the ſame ſufferings which we alſo ſuffer.</hi> The Salvation of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> was effectual, that is powerfully promoted, effectually carried by enduring the ſame ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which the Apoſtle endured. Hence the World through Chriſt is ſaid to be ours, as well as all other things. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23. Becauſe even the troubles of the World are
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102520:35"/>through Chriſt made to work for our advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>§. The interceſſion of Chriſt, a ground of comfort againſt the troubles of the World.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The interceſſion of Chriſt is a ground of comfort againſt the troubles of the World. <hi>Joh</hi> 17.9, 13. <hi>I pray for them whom thou haſt given me — And theſe things I ſpeak in the VVorld, that they might have my joy fulfilled in themſelves.</hi> He acquainted them with his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, on purpoſe that their hearts might be filled with joy. It is a comfort to ſuch as are in affliction to hear that good men are always mindful of them in their Prayers to God. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6, 7. <hi>You have a good remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of us alwayes — Therefore Brethren we were comforted over you in all our affliction and diſtreſs by your Faith.</hi> If it were good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to the Apoſtle to hear that the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> had good remembrance of him always, and that which did comfort him in all his afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtreſs. How much more may it comfort us in all our affliction and diſtreſs to hear that Jeſus Chriſt hath good remembrance of us alwayes, and ever liveth to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us. For
<list>
                        <item>(1.) Though Chriſt be in Heaven and we are upon the Earth, he beareth us upon his heart continually. This was typified by the high Prieſt under the Law, <hi>Aaron</hi> bore the names and the judgment of the Children of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102520:36"/>
                           <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon his heart continually, when he went into the holy place; <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.29, 30. <hi>And</hi> Aaron <hi>ſhall bear the names of the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>upon the Breaſt plate of judgment upon his heart, when he goeth in unto the holy place for a memorial before the Lord continually — And ſhall bear the judgment of the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>before the Lord continually. Aaron</hi> the high Prieſt was a Type of Chriſt who is our great high Prieſt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Aarons</hi> going in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy place was a Type of Chriſts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending into Heaven. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. What <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> did Typically when he entred into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place, that Chriſt doth really for us now he is in Heaven. And what was it that <hi>Aaron</hi> did when he went into the holy place.
<list>
                              <item>1. He bore the names, and he bore the judgment of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon his heart. The judgment of the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> may ſignifie all their cauſes, their affairs, their condition; this teacheth us, Chriſt our high Prieſt knoweth his by name, and that both their perſons and conditions are born up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his heart.</item>
                              <item>2 <hi>Aaron</hi> bore the names and judgments of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon his heart at all times when he went into the holy place; twice it is mentioned, that he bore them continually which teacheth us that neither our perſons or conditions are at any time forgotten of Chriſt, but they are upon his heart continually now that he is in Heaven. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.23. <hi>I am conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102520:36"/>with thee.</hi> That is, continually upon thy heart, under thy care. And as <hi>David</hi> was, ſo are we continually with Chriſt.</item>
                              <item>3. <hi>Aaron</hi> bore both the names and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for a memorial before the Lord continually. So Chriſt our high Prieſt, as he carrieth our perſons and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions upon his own heart, ſo he continually preſenteth our caſe and condition before his Father. The Apoſtle ſaid, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.3. <hi>You are in our hearts to die and live with you.</hi> The like may be ſaid of Chriſt concerning all that are his; They are ſo much in the heart of Chriſt that he dyed for them, and now that he is raiſed from the dead, they are ſo much on his heart that he will live with them for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. The Church of Chriſt is more upon the heart of Chriſt than the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was upon <hi>Pauls</hi> heart. Now if the Saints had ſuch a Room in <hi>Pauls</hi> heart, that it was in his heart to live and dye with them, then how much are all the Saints upon the heart of Chriſt. What the Lord ſaith of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Mine Eyes and mine Heart ſhall be there perpetually.</hi> The ſame is true of all Chriſtians that are the Temple of God. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Ye are the Temple of the Living God.</hi> The eyes of the Lord and the heart of the Lord ſhall be upon them perpetually. Chriſts bearing us upon his heart is ſet forth by his carrying his Lambs in his Boſom. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.11. <hi>He ſhall feed his Flock like a Shepherd, he
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102520:37"/>ſhall gather the Lambs with his Arm, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them in his Boſom.</hi> It is not ſaid, he ſhall put them but he ſhall carry them in his Boſom, intimating that not only ſtrong Chriſtians, but the weakeſt and moſt feeble, and ſhiftleſs are always born upon his heart. And in doing this he fulfills his Peoples Prayers, for they deſire to be ſet as a Seal upon the heart of Chriſt <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Set me as a Seal upon thine heart, as a Seal upon thine Arm.</hi> The Seal makes and leaves an impreſſion upon the Wax, and all the cuts and engravings on the Seal are imprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Wax, 'tis as if the Spouſe ſhould have ſaid, carry me upon thy heart as men uſe to carry Seals which they are very chary of, and that there be deep and abiding impreſſions of all my troubles graven upon thy heart, ſet me as a Seal upon thine Arm, that is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the love of thine heart by thy actings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me and for me, put forth thy power to help me in all my troubles. The Apoſtle had great confidence that God would give pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving grace to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> becauſe they were much in his heart to pray for them every time he went to the Throne of Grace. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.4, 6, 7. <hi>Always in every Prayer of mine for you all, making requeſt with joy — Being confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of this very thing, that he which hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun a good work in you, will perform it untill the day of Jeſus Chriſt; even as it is meet for me to think this of you all, becauſe I have you in my heart.</hi> If the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had ſuch confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102520:37"/>of the <hi>Philippians</hi> welfare, becauſe he had them in his heart, what confidence may we have in all our troubles, from Chriſts having us in his heart, and bearing us upon his heart continually, and ever living to make interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>(2) Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in his interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on repreſents to his Father our troubles and dangers that we are expoſed to while we are in the World, and our ſhiftleſs condition, and the hatred we meet with from the World, and prays his Father to keep us by his divine power, he prays not that we ſhould be taken out of the World while we have ſervice to do in the World, but that we may be kept from the evils, we are liable to in the World. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.9.11, 14, 15. Where obſerve
<list>
                              <item>1. The Perſons for whom Chriſt interceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and they are all that are his; <hi>ver.</hi> 9.10. <hi>I pray for them: I pray not for the World, but for them which thou haſt given me, for they are thine, and all mine are thine, and thine are mine.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. He repreſents to his Father, the dangers they are in by being in the World, where they are hated, and want his preſence with them. <hi>ver.</hi> 11.14. <hi>And now I am no more in the world, but theſe are in the world — I have given them thy Word, and the world hath hated them.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>3. He commits them to his Fathers care, and prays him to keep them by his divine power. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>Holy Father, keep through
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102520:38"/>thine own Name, thoſe whom thou haſt given me.</hi> That which he mainly prayed for, was not that they ſhould be taken out of the world, but kept from the evil. <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>I pray not that thou ſhouldſt take them out of the World, but keep them from the evil.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>4. The Arguments he uſeth in Prayer, they are all mine, and all thine, and they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie me. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>All mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>5. This Prayer of Chriſt for his, wherein he hath prayed to his Father to keep them in his name, whilſt they are in this world was recorded on purpoſe to comfort our hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our troubles. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>Theſe things I ſpeak in the world, that they may have my joy fulfilled in themſelves.</hi> And this Prayer of Chriſt was made not only for his Diſciples, that were then living, but for all, that ſhould afterward believe on him to the end of the World. <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo, which ſhall believe on me through their word.</hi> And what Chriſt prayed for, God will aſſuredly grant. <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.42. <hi>I know that thou heareſt me always.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But how is the interceſſion of Chriſt a ground of comfort againſt the troubles of the world, when notwithſtanding the Prayer of Chriſt, that they, that are his, may be kept from the evil they fall into as many and as great troubles as other men?</p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:102520:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Many troubles and afflictions are kept off, at the interceſſion of Chriſt, from thoſe that are his; For ſuch is the malice of Satan and wicked men againſt the Saints, that they would do them an hundred fold more miſchief than they do, if God ſhould not reſtrain them, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 124.2.3, 4, 5. <hi>Laban</hi> would have done <hi>Jacob</hi> much hurt; but God would not ſuffer him to hurt him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.7. <hi>Your Father hath deceived me, and changed my wages ten times, but God ſuffered him not to hurt me.</hi> The <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> when few in number, when they went up and down from one place and one Kingdom to another, were liable to many injuries, but God prevented the malice of their adverſaries. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14. <hi>He ſuffered no man to do them wrong.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. When God doth not keep off troubles and afflictions from the Members of Chriſt, which is not abſolutely prayed for, God at the interceſſion of Chriſt keeps off the evil of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from the members of Chriſt. The evil of trouble is, when troubles make us ſin againſt God, and forſake the ways of God. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.21. <hi>VVhen Tribulation or Perſecution ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth becauſe of thy word, by and by he is offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> that is, falleth away as another Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt expreſſeth it. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Behold this evil is of the Lord, why ſhould I wait for the Lord any longer.</hi> The evil of troubles is when men fret, and curſe, and blaſpheme the name of God becauſe of their troubles; as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.21.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102520:39"/>
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10.11. Now the Members of Chriſt are kept from theſe evils under their troubles.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. At the interceſſion of Chriſt the nature of troubles and afflictions are changed, they are not evils but good things to the People of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. <hi>It is good for me that I have been afflicted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. At the interceſſion of Chriſt they that are Chriſts are upheld under their troubles, and kept from fainting. <hi>Keep through thine own name thoſe, whom thou haſt given me.</hi> Though we be not kept from trouble, yet Chriſts Prayer is anſwered, if we be kept by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God in our troubles, kept from falling, kept from fainting. Now God, for Chriſts ſake, keeps his people from falling and fainting under their troubles. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.18. <hi>VVhen I ſaid, my Foot ſlippeth: thy Mercy, O Lord, held me up. Pſal.</hi> 116.8. <hi>Thou haſt delivered my feet from falling — Pſal.</hi> 118.13. <hi>Thou haſt thruſt ſore at me that I might fall: but the Lord helped me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) The interceſſion of Chriſt is a ground of comfort under all our troubles, becauſe he interceedeth with his Father, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the comforter, may be ſent down into our hearts, to abide with us for ever. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.1.16, 17. <hi>Let not your heart be troubled — I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102520:39"/>even the Spirit of Truth.</hi> The Lord Jeſus foreſeeing that his Diſciples would meet with many Tribulations, that their hearts might not be troubled, propoſeth many grounds of comfort to them, among others this is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal one, that he would interceed with his Father to give them his holy Spirit to be their Comforter, to make his abode with them for ever. But ſome may ſay, though the Spirit, the Comforter, be ſent down into our hearts to abide with us for ever, yet many of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt that have the comforter, want the comforts of the Spirit in their troubles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What ſhall we do that we may get the comforts of the Spirit in our afflictions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Walk in the fear of God, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore trouble comes, and when you walk in the midſt of trouble, for ſuch as walk in the fear of God, enjoy the comforts of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.31. <hi>VValking in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Give your ſelves to prayer in the day of trouble. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.24. <hi>Ask, and ye ſhall recieve, that your joy may be full.</hi> Chriſt told his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. That they ſhould weep, and lament, and be ſorrowful, but their forrow ſhould be turned into joy, and here he directs them the way to get comfort under their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, which was by Praver, <hi>Ask, and ye ſhall recieve, that your joy may be full.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Call to mind, apply, and meditate upon the gracious promiſes of God. The Spirit
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102520:40"/>comforts us by and through the word, and more eſpecially by the promiſes. It was through the word that <hi>David</hi> had the Spirits comforts in his affliction. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49, 50. <hi>Remember thy word unto thy Servant, wherein thou haſt cauſed me to hope this is my comfort in mine affliction.</hi> So alſo the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had the comforts of the Spirit through the word. <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Thy words were found, and I did eat them, and thy word was unto me the joy and the rejoycing of my heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Keep up, and act your Faith in God through Chriſt in all your troubles, for truſtings in God brings the joys and comforts of the Holy Ghoſt into our hearts. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.5. <hi>I have truſted in thy Mercy, my heart ſhall rejoyce in thy Salvation.</hi> In the 3d. verſe he complained of his ſorrows, that he had ſorrows in his heart dayly, but having ſtrengthned his Faith by the conſideration of the mercy of God, he concluded that God would put joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into his heart. <hi>My heart ſhall rejoyce — Rom.</hi> 15.13. <hi>The God of Peace fill you with all joy and peace in believing</hi> — There is joy, all joy, a fulneſs of all joy comes in by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving.</p>
                  <p n="4">(4.) The interceſſion of Chriſt is a ground of comfort againſt the troubles of the world, becauſe it is our ſecurity that they ſhall not cauſe our Faith to fail. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.31, 32. <hi>And the Lord ſaid, Simon, Simon, behold Satan hath deſired to have you, that he may ſift you as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102520:40"/>Wheat: but I have prayed for thee, that thy Faith fail not. — Peter</hi> was greatly affrighted at the ſufferings of Chriſt. The fear of the Croſs made him fall in a dreadful manner, three times he denyed his Maſter, and curſed, and ſwore that he did not know the man. But though he was grievouſly foiled, yet by the Prayer of Chriſt his Faith was ſupported that it did not fail. Not only our Fleſh and our Hearts would fail, but our Faith alſo, if it were not preſerved by the interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>§ All troubles are ſanctified to thoſe that are Chriſts. This is a ground of great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. All troubles and afflictions, whatſoever befall thoſe that are Chriſts, are ſanctified to them, and ſhall work together for their good, and this is a ground of comfort under all the troubles of this World, that they ſhall be ſanctified to us, and work for our good. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is made, of God, Sanctification to all ſuch as are in him. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>But of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us VViſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption.</hi> When Chriſt is ſaid to be made of God, ſanctification to ſuch as are in him, the meaning is, that he is appointed by God to ſanctifie our perſons and our conditions. Our Lord Jeſus hath taken the curſe from our Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and turned them into Bleſſings. So that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:102520:41"/>we are not now to look upon our corrections, as our miſery; but rather as conducing to our happineſs. <hi>Job.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Behold happy is the man whom God correcteth.</hi> That all our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſanctified by Jeſus Chriſt appeareth thus, becauſe none of them ſhall do us hurt, but they ſhall all work together for our good. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>And we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi> There is a threeſold good which is wrought for us by our afflictions.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. They purge out our ſins. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.9. <hi>By this therefore ſhall the iniquity of Jacob be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and this is all the fruit to take away their ſin.</hi> And this is greatly for our good to be purged from our ſins, which are the chiefeſt of evils.</item>
                     <item>2. They promote and increaſe the graces of the Spirit of God in our hearts, and make us partakers of his Holineſs, and that is much for our profit to be made more Holy. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10. <hi>They verily for a few days chaſtned us after their own pleaſure, but he for our profit, that we might be partakers of his Holineſs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. They encreaſe our glory in the world to come for ever. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>For our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>nal weight of glory.</hi> Now the knowledge of this, that all our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are ſent to do us good, and that they ſhall all work together for our good, is a ground
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102520:41"/>of great comfort under all our troubles. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3, 4. <hi>VVe glory in Tribulations alſo, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Tribulation worketh Patience; and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience Experience, and Experience Hope.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> exhorteth us to count it joy, yea all joy when we fall into divers temptations, becauſe we know that our Tryals ſhall work patience in us. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>My Brethren count it all joy when ye fall into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Temptations, knowing this, that the trying of your Faith worketh Patience.</hi> Now if this ſingle benefit, the encreaſing of our Patience, be ſuch a ground of joy, how may it encreaſe our joy, when we conſider that not only Patience, but our other graces alſo, and not our graces but our glory in Heaven ſhall be augmented for ever, by our momentary afflictions which we go through in this World. The Apoſtle writing to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> encourageth to chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in their ſufferings, becauſe they were for their profit. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10, 11. <hi>He chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth us for our profit — Wherefore lift up the hands that hang down, and the feeble knees.</hi> Though a man was in a dejected condition, with hands hanging down, and in a fainting condition, his knees waxing feeble under his burdens, yet the conſideration that he is chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for his profit may revive him, and make him lift up his hands that hang down, and ſtrengthen his feeble knees.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:102520:42"/>
                  <p>§. The Lord Jeſus will not leave us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſs in our troubles. How Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts his people.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. Though we meet with many troubles in the World, this may chear our hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all of them, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath promiſed, he will not leave us comfortleſs in our troubles, but he will give us peace and comfort in himſelf, and from himſelf when we meet with troubles in the World. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.18. <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſs, I will come to you. Joh.</hi> 16.33. <hi>Theſe things I have ſpoken unto you, that in me ye might have peace, in the world ye ſhall have Tribulation. Iſa.</hi> 66.13. <hi>As one whom his Mother comforteth, ſo will I comfort you, and ye ſhall be comforted in Jeruſalem.</hi> The Affections of a Mother are very great and tender towards her Child, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially towards her ſick and afflicted Child, ſhe will ſpare no pains, no coſt for that which may comfort her ſick Child. The affections of a Nurſe are great. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7, 8. But of a Mother far greater. Now as readily, as affectionately as a Mother comforts her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Child, ſo hath the Lord promiſed to comfort his afflicted people. <hi>And ye ſhall be comforted in</hi> Jeruſalem. That is to be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for this Prophet had foretold great judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and deſolations ſhould come upon <hi>Jera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> As <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Jeruſalem is ruined, and Judah is fallen. Iſa.</hi> 24.3, 11. <hi>The Land ſhall be utterly emptied, and utterly ſpoyled. All
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102520:42"/>joy is darkned, and the mirth of the Land is gone. Iſa.</hi> 64.10. <hi>Thy Holy Cities are a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, Zion is a Wilderneſs, Jeruſalem a deſolation.</hi> Yet though theſe Ruines and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations were coming upon <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that the Land ſhould be utterly ſpoiled, all joy be darkned, and the mirth of the Land quite gone; yet the Lord promiſeth to comfort his people in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> We that have ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, may reſt upon God, that for Chriſts ſake he will comfort us in all our tribulations. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.8. <hi>VVhen I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me.</hi> Afflictions and troubles are ſet out by the name of darkneſs. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.7. Joy and Comfort are expreſſed by the name of light, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.11. So that the meaning is, when I am in trouble and diſtreſs, the Lord ſhall give me comfort. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 38.7. <hi>Though I walk in the midſt of trouble, thou wilt revive me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But do we not ſee, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing theſe promiſes, and the confidences of the people of God, that God will comfort them in their afflictions; yet they are oft times un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der very great ſorrows and heavineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. The people of God have Fleſh, as well as Spirit; though the Spirit be willing to love the croſs, the Fleſh is weak, though the Spirit rejoyceth in God, the Fleſh feeling the ſmart of the Rod, mourns.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:102520:43"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Their ſorrows do not laſt alwayes, but are ſoon turned into joy. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Ye ſhall weep and lament—but your ſorrow ſhall be turned into joy.</hi> Chriſt doth not promiſe his Diſciples, that they ſhall have no ſorrows, no cauſe of weeping; but this he promiſeth, that they ſhall not be left comfortleſs under their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, for their ſorrow ſhall be turned into joy. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5, 11. <hi>VVeeping may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Even while the people of God are mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they are ſowing the ſeeds of joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and ſhall doubtleſs reap the fruit of their ſorrows in more abundant conſolations. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 126.5, 6. <hi>They that ſow in tears, ſhall reap in joy. He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious ſeed, ſhall doubtleſs come again with rejoyceing, bringing his ſheaves with him.</hi> There is much more reaped than was ſown: A little quantity of ſeed yields whole Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loads of Corn.</p>
                  <p>To open this more fully, of Chriſts promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing not to leave his people comfortleſs in their troubles: I will ſhew you ſeveral wayes, whereby Chriſt comforts his Members, and gives them peace under their greateſt troubles.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By ſhedding abroad the love of God in their hearts, by the Holy Ghoſt, which he gives unto them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3, 5. <hi>VVe glory in tribulation—becauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts, by the Holy Ghoſt, which is given
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102520:43"/>unto us.</hi> By ſhedding abroad the love of God in our hearts, underſtand the manifeſting of Gods love to our ſouls, the giving us the knowledge and underſtanding of the love of God, which doth wonderfully affect the heart with joy and gladneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.7, 8. <hi>All thy waves and thy billows are gone over me, yet the Lord will command his loving kindneſs in the day time, and in the night, his Song ſhall be with me.</hi> Two things are here worthy of our obſervation.
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>David</hi> did believe, that in his greateſt diſtreſſes, when all Gods waves and billows went over him, God would expreſs and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his love to him—<hi>yet the Lord will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his loving kindneſs.</hi> The commanding his loving kindneſs, implyeth the powerful expreſſions of his love. <hi>VVhere the word of a King is, there is power. Eccl.</hi> 8.4. And the abiding impreſſions of his love. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 33.9. <hi>He commanded, and it ſtood faſt.</hi> And the ſpeedy manifeſtation of his love. For when God gives a command to things to be done, it implyeth ſpeed. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 147.15. <hi>He ſendeth forth his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment upon the Earth, his word runneth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſwiftly.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>David</hi> did believe that the manifeſtation of the love of God would be ſuch a comfort to him, that it would make his heart to ſing for joy in his greateſt diſtreſſes; yet the Lord ſhall command his loving kindneſs, and in the night his ſong ſhall be with me.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:102520:44"/>
                     <item>2. Jeſus Chriſt comforts and refreſheth his Members in their troubles, by thoſe gracious viſits which he gives them in their afflictions. <hi>Job.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Thy viſitation hath preſerved my Spirit. John</hi> 16.22. <hi>And ye now have ſorrow, but I will ſee you again, and your heart ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and your joy no man taketh from you.</hi> A viſit from a good man is very comfortable in a day of trouble. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5, 6. <hi>Our fleſh had no reſt, we were troubled on every ſide, without were fightings, within were fears. Nevertheleſs God that comforteth them that are caſt down, comforted us by the coming of Titus.</hi> If a viſit from a good man be ſo refreſhing, that it will comfort us when we are troubled on every ſide, when we have fightings without, and fears within, then how comfortable is a viſit from Chriſt in the day of trouble. But how doth Chriſt viſit his afflicted people? what are thoſe viſits of Chriſt, which he gives his people in their affliction.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Chriſt viſiteth his people with his word, by bringing ſuitable and encouraging pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to them in a day of diſtreſs. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.54, 57. <hi>Waters flowed over mine head, then I ſaid I am cut off—Thou dreweſt near in the day that I called upon thee, thou ſaideſt, fear not.</hi> Thus the Lord viſited <hi>Abraham</hi> with a ſuitable word of promiſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. <hi>After theſe things the word of the Lord came to Abraham in a Viſion, ſaying, Fear not Abraham, I am thy ſhield, and thy exceeding great reward.</hi> And theſe are
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102520:44"/>ſweet viſits which do greatly rejoyce the heart. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.162. <hi>I rejoyce at thy word, as one that findeth great ſpoil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt viſiteth his people in their afflictions, by his Spirit, the teachings, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivings, the ſupports of his Spirit. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6. <hi>His left hand is under my head, his right hand doth embrace me. Iſa</hi> 41.10. <hi>Fear thou not, for I am with thee— I will ſtrengthen thee, I will uphold thee. Iſa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>I dwell with him that is of a contrite and an humble Spirit, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the Spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Lord Jeſus viſits his afflicted people when he anſwers their Prayers, and fulfils his own promiſes. <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.1. <hi>And the Lord vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited Sarah as he had ſaid, and the Lord did unto Sarah as he had ſpoken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Lord viſits his afflicted people, when he raiſeth up deliverance for them out of their troubles. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.4. <hi>O viſit me with thy Salvation.</hi> And ſuch viſits when God ſaves his people out of their troubles cauſe great joy. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.1. <hi>The King ſhall joy in thy ſtrength, O Lord, and in thy Salvation how greatly ſhall he rejoyce?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. As Chriſt comforts his afflicted people by the gracious viſits which he gives them, ſo alſo by raiſing and ſtrengthning their Faith in times of trouble, and cauſing them to ſtay themſelves upon God in an evil day: For the ſtaying the mind upon God is a means to keep
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102520:45"/>the Soul in peace under the greateſt dangers. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3. <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace whoſe mind is ſtayed on thee, becauſe he truſteth in thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Jeſus Chriſt comforteth his afflicted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the hope of Eternal Life, which he promiſeth to ſuch as are in a ſuffering condition, if they continue faithful to the death. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer, be thou faithful unto Death, and I will give thee a Crown of Life.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>If we ſuffer, we ſhall alſo reign with him. Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>And rejoyce in hope of the glory of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. If an intereſt in Chriſt be ſuch a ground of Conſolation, then here is reproof.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) For thoſe that content themſelves with a Worldly Intereſt, and take no care no pains to get an intereſt in Chriſt, but neglect Chriſt. Such mens caſe is ſad, For
<list>
                           <item>1. The world is a poor portion, for all worldly enjoyments abſtracted from God and Chriſt are nothing but vanity and vexation of Spirit.</item>
                           <item>2. All the world will avail a man nothing when he comes to dye. It will give no eaſe to a troubled Conſcience, no pardon of Sin, no help to Heaven. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.7. <hi>We can car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nothing of it away with us into another world.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. They that have neglected Chriſt and the Salvation purchaſed by Chriſt, ſhall not eſcape the wrath of God in the other World. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:102520:45"/>
                     <item>(2.) For thoſe that have an intereſt in Chriſt, and yet live very diſcontentedly; either for want of ſome things which they deſire, as Parts, Riches, Friends, a ſetled Condition, or for the loſs of ſome things; which God hath taken away from them, or becauſe of ſome croſſes or troubles that they meet with in the World.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. Of Examination, Have we a true ſaving intereſt in Chriſt? can we ſay Chriſt is ours and we are his?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> How may we know, whither Chriſt be ours?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. If we love him. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My Beloved is mine;</hi> and if our love to him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed our love to all other things, and perſons in the World, if he be our beſt Beloved. Chriſt doth not own thoſe as having an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt him, that love any thing above him. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37. <hi>He that loveth Father or Mother more than me, is not worthy of me.</hi> That ſuch as love God and Chriſt above all things, have a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, is evident, becauſe eternal Life is promiſed to them. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Heirs of the Kingdom which God hath promiſed to thoſe that love him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> How ſhall we know that we love Chriſt above all things?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. When we deſire Chriſt above all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102520:46"/>things in the world. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25. So that if God ſhould ask us, as he did <hi>Solomon,</hi> what ſhall I give thee? we would ſay, Lord, give us thy ſelf for our God, and thy Son for our Saviour.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When we eſteem Chriſt above all things, ſo as that we count them as dung, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, and are willing to part with any thing, ſo that we may win Chriſt. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. VVhen the love of God in Chriſt puts more joy and gladneſs into our hearts, than the enjoyment of all the world; or, it would be a greater joy to us, than the whole world; if God would manifeſt his love to us. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>(2.) If we are Chriſts, then Chriſt is ours; that's another Character in the Text. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am his.</hi> Now we may know we are Chriſts.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. If we have ſolemnly given up our ſelves to Chriſt, with a ſincere heart, without any ſecret reſerves of any Luſt, reſolving that by the help of his grace we will deny our ſelves, take up our Croſs, and follow him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Mark</hi> 8.34.</item>
                     <item>2. If his intereſt will prevail with us beyond our own intereſt, and his will above our own wills; if his word be our rule, and his glory our end, that is a good evidence that we are Chriſts. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.19. <hi>VVe are thine, thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beareſt rule over them.</hi> As much as to ſay, they are the Lords, over whom the Lord
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102520:46"/>bears rule. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.94. <hi>I am thine — I have ſought thy precepts.</hi> When in doubtful Caſes we ſeek out the will of Chriſt, and follow the will of Chriſt, that ſhews us to be his.</item>
                     <item>3. When we are Chriſts Servants. <hi>Act.</hi> 27. 23. <hi>VVhoſe I am, and whom I ſerve.</hi> And the great end why we deſire to live, is to do ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for Chriſt. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21.</item>
                     <item>4. When we are tender and careful of Chriſts glory. <hi>John</hi> 17.10. I am glorified in them that are mine and thine.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>(3.) The Spirit of Chriſt ſent down into our Hearts, is a certain Evidence of an intereſt in Chriſt. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.24. <hi>Hereby we know, that he abideth in us, by the Spirit that he hath given us. Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall we know that we have the Spirit of Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. If we have an obediential frame of heart. <hi>Ezek</hi> 36.27. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 7. The carnal heart is enmity to the Law of God, and therefore when we are cauſed to obey Gods Statutes, that is from the Spirit put within us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We may know we have the Spirit, by the fruits of the Spirit, which are Faith, Love, Peace, Joy, Long-ſuffering, <hi>&amp;c. Gal.</hi> 5. 22, 23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> III. Of <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exhort.</hi> 1. To ſuch as want an intereſt in Chriſt, that they would above all things ſeek
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102520:47"/>to get Chriſt. What <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith of <hi>Wiſdom Prov.</hi> 4.7. The ſame may I ſay of Jeſus Chriſt, who is called the Wiſdom of God. Jeſus Chriſt is the principal thing, therefore above all things, get Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exhort.</hi> 2. To ſuch as have an intereſt in Chriſt, to labour for the knowledge of it, that every one may be able to ſay, Chriſt is mine, and I am his.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall we attain to the knowledge of our intereſt in Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Examine your ſelves by thoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters the Scripture gives of an intereſt in Chriſt, and more particularly about your Faith. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. And if you cannot make any clear work hereof at one time, try what you can do at another.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Pray earneſtly to God, to manifeſt your intereſt in Chriſt. It is in his light that we ſee light. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. Pray as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 35.3. <hi>Say unto my Soul, I am thy Salvation.</hi> And if you can't obtain the knowledge of your inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Chriſt, by much ſeeking to God, yet follow on to ſeek him, and then in Gods good time, you ſhall know the Lord to be your God in Chriſt. <hi>Hoſ</hi> 6.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.9. <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Accuſtom your ſelf to truſt in God in all your ſtraits, fears, dangers, and temptations. For the more you truſt in God, the ſooner you ſhall come to the knowledge of your intereſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102520:47"/>in God <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.1, 2. <hi>[In thee do I put my truſt] O my Soul, thou hast ſaid unto the Lord, [thou art my Lord] Pſal.</hi> 31.14. <hi>But I truſted in thee, O Lord, I ſaid thou art my God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Learn to deny your ſelves for Chriſt: for the more you are exercifed in ſelf-denial, the ſooner you ſhall attain to know your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt. After <hi>Abraham</hi> had denyed himſelf of taking a reward from the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> God came to him with a promiſe, to aſſure him of his intereſt in God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. <hi>After theſe things the word of the Lord came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Abraham in a Viſion, ſaying, Fear not Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, I am thy ſhield, and thy exceeding great reward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Set your love upon Chriſt. The Spouſe finding in her heart an ardent love to Chriſt, could ſay, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My Beloved is mine.</hi> To ſuch as love Chriſt, there is a promiſe, that he will manifeſt himſelf to their Souls. <hi>John</hi> 14.21.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Labour to order your Converſation aright, and to live righteouſly and holily. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.17.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Attend frequently that ſealing ordinance of the Lords upper; the neglect or careleſs uſe whereof, is the reaſon ſo few Chriſtians at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to aſſurance of their intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exhort.</hi> 3. Learn how to fetch comfort from Chriſt in all troubles. How to retain the knowledge of your intereſt in Chriſt. VVhat you ſhould do, that can't make out
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102520:48"/>your intereſt in Chriſt in a day of trouble, and at an hour of death.</p>
                  <p>I have ſhewn that there is comfort to be had in Chriſt, for ſuch as have an intereſt in him, not only under outward, but alſo under Soul troubles. Now I ſhall conclude this diſcourſe, with the reſolution of three queſtions.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. How may we fetch comfort from Chriſt in all our troubles.</item>
                     <item>2. How may ſuch as have attained the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lede of their intereſt in Chriſt, retain the ſame.</item>
                     <item>3. VVhat ſhall they do, that want the knowledge of their intereſt in Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. How may we fetch comfort from Chriſt in all our troubles, both inward and outward.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Get Acquaintance with Chriſt, and thoſe benefits we have by Chriſt. The more we have of the knowledge of Chriſt, the more peace and comfort we ſhall have in our Souls. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Grace and peace be multiplyed unto you, through the knowledge of God, and of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> As grace, ſo peace alſo is mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, given abundantly through the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and Jeſus Chriſt. And as the knowledge of Chriſt tends much to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of peace and comfort, ſo alſo doth the knowledge of the benefits that we have by Chriſt, very much promote our comfort un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all our troubles, as I might ſhew, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102520:48"/>in the ſeveral benefits we have by Chriſt, I will mention three or four.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) By Chriſt we are reconciled to God, and have an attonement made for our Souls. <hi>God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> The knowledge of this attonement which Chriſt hath made for us, will fill our hearts with joy and gladneſs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11. <hi>We joy in God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom we have now received the attonement.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(2.) By Chriſt we have remiſſion of all our ſins. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.38, 39. And the knowledge of remiſſion of ſins is a ground of joy in all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.2. <hi>Son, be of good chear, thy ſins are forgiven thee.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(3.) By Chriſt, our perſons and ſervices are accepted of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6. And the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of our perſons and ſervices, may put great joy and gladneſs into our hearts. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy Wine with a merry heart, for God now accepteth thy works.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(4.) By Jeſus Chriſt, we have a perfect, and compleat righteouſneſs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. And this is matter of great joy. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. <hi>I will great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyce in the Lord, my Soul ſhall be joyful in my God, for he hath cloathed me with the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Salvation, he hath covered me with the robe of righteouſneſs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(5.) By Chriſt, we have boldneſs to hope for eternal life. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19. And hope of eternal life, is a ground of great joy in all our
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102520:49"/>troubles. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>We rejoyce in hope of the glory of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(6.) By Chriſt there is a new Covenant eſtabliſhed, full of precious promiſes. And the knowledge of the Covenant layeth a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for peace and comfort in all troubles. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.13, 14. <hi>His Soul ſhall dwell at eaſe —He wil ſhew them his Covenant.</hi> To be at eaſe, intimates a relief againſt all ſorts of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidies, for if there be any thing that diſquiets the Soul, it is not at eaſe. Dwelling at eaſe, implyeth a permanency of Spiritual comforts. Now here comes the Soul to dwell at eaſe, when the outward man is expoſed to variety of troubles? It is by being acquainted with the Covenant.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="2">II. If you would fetch comfort from Chriſt under all troubles, get, and keep clear appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of your intereſt in Chriſt, and in thoſe benefits which he hath purchaſed with his blood. Darkneſs and doubts about our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt hinder our comfort, but when we know Chriſt to be ours, our Saviour, and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; this will make our Souls greatly to rejoyce under all our troubles. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.47. <hi>My Spirit hath rejoyced in God my Saviour.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. <hi>David was greatly diſtreſſed, for the people ſpake of ſtoning him — But David en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged himſelf in the Lord his God. Pſ.</hi> 27. 1. <hi>The Lord is my light and my Salvation, whom ſhall I fear? The Lord is the ſtrength of my Life, of whom ſhall I be afraid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:102520:49"/>
                  <p n="3">III. Keep in remembrance, and meditate on the benefits you have by Chriſt, as Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God, Remiſſion of ſins, Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Sanctification, Eternal life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For thoſe things that are forgotten, and out of mind, yield no comfort to us. It is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance and meditating on Chriſt, and the benefits of Chriſt, that brings in ſweetneſs, and Soul-ſatisfying comforts. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.34. <hi>My meditation of him ſhall be ſweet. Pſ.</hi> 63.5, 6. <hi>My Soul ſhall be ſatisfied, as with marrow and fatneſs; when I remember thee upon my bed, and meditate on thee in the night watches. Pſ.</hi> 94. 19. <hi>In the multitude of my thoughts within me, thy comforts delight my Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. In all your troubles, both inward and outward, keep up your Faith in Chriſt, and in God, through Chriſt. Truſt in God, that for Chriſts ſake, he will give you all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings purchaſed with the blood of Chriſt, and promiſed in the new Covenant. For this is the way to keep your hearts from being trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and to fill your Souls with peace and joy. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing. Iſa.</hi> 26.3. <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whoſe mind is ſtayed on thee, becauſe he truſteth in thee.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>In whom, though now ye ſee him not, yet believing, ye rejoyce with joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and full of glory. John</hi> 14.1. <hi>Let not your heart be troubled: ye believe in God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve alſo in me.</hi> Upon hearing this Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:102520:50"/>let not your hearts be troubled, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples might have replyed, Lord, haſt thou not told us that in the world we ſhall have tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that we ſhall be hated of all men, for thy names ſake, and that we ſhall be caſt out of the Synagogue, and that men ſhall lay hands on us, and put us into Priſons; and we ſhall be brought before Kings and Rulers, and that men will think, they do God good ſervice, when they kill us: How ſhall we keep our hearts from being troubled, when all theſe troubles come upon us? As a remedy againſt their hearts being troubled; he bids them believe on God, and on himſelf. <hi>Believe on God, believe alſo on me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">V. In all your diſtreſſes, give your ſelves to Prayer, for that is the way to be filled with comforts, and to have your ſorrows turned into joy. <hi>John</hi> 16.20, 24. <hi>Verily, Verily, I ſay unto you, that ye ſhall weep, and lament, but the world ſhall rejoyce, and ye ſhall be ſorrowful, but your ſorrow ſhall be turned into joy.</hi> And what counſell and direction doth he give them, that their ſorrow may be turned into joy? It is to give themſelves unto Prayer. <hi>Ask, and ye ſhall recieve, that your joy may be full.</hi> The like direction the Apoſtle gives us for keeping our minds from all kind of troubleſome cares, and for the obtaining that peace, which paſſeth all underſtanding, and that is, to give our ſelves to Prayer <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>Be careful for nothing: but in every thing by prayer and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:102520:50"/>with thanksgiving, let your requeſts be made known unto God. And the peace of Goà which paſſeth all underſtanding, ſhall keep your hearts and minds through Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">VI. Let the word of Chriſt dwell richly in your hearts, that you may have ſome ſuitable promiſes, to have recourſe unto in all your troubles, for that will give you abiding peace, and ſtrong Conſolation in all your troubles. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.15, 16. <hi>Let the peace of God rule in your hearts</hi>— But ſome may ſay, how ſhall we attain to this, to have the peace of God rule in our hearts? the following words ſhew this, <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all Wiſdom.</hi> By the peace of God we may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, not only that peace which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to have one with another, but that peace which God gives in our own hearts and Conſciences, as it is taken. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. Then the peace of God rules in our hearts, when it keeps our hearts quiet, under all troubles, ſo as no troubles are able to diſturb and break our peace. Now the way to attain to this is, to let the word of Chriſt dwell in us richly in all Wiſdom. Then the word of Chriſt dwells with us, when it abides in our hearts, we are acquainted with it, and we converſe daily with it, as we do with thoſe that dwell in the ſame houſe with us. Then it dwels in us richly, when we are well ſtored with the promiſes of the word, when we have promiſes ſuitable to every condition, and every trouble that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102520:51"/>we paſs through. Then it dwells with us in all Wiſdom, when we have the right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, and know how to make uſe of it upon all occaſions, as we ſtand in need of it. It was by the word that <hi>David</hi> found comfort in all his afflictions. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 49, 50. <hi>Remember thy word unto thy Servant, upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope.</hi> It was alſo from the word of God, that <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had his comforts under his greateſt ſorrows, when he complained that his pain was perpetual, and his wound incurable. <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Thy words were found, and I did eat them, and thy word was unto me the joy and rejoycing of mine heart.</hi> And that it was a time of great diſtreſs with the Prophet, when Gods word was the joy and rejoycing of his heart, is evident from <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Why is my pain perpetual, and my wound incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that refuſeth to be healed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">VII. Walk in the fear of God, and hold faſt your integrity in all your troubles, and then you ſhall have the comforts of the Holy Ghoſt, and the light of Conſolation ſhall ariſe upon you in the darkeſt days. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.31. <hi>Walking in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt. Pſal.</hi> 112.4. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright there ariſeth Light in Darkneſs.</hi> Though you ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake, yet love Righteouſnes and hate Iniquity, and in ſo doing, the Lord will anoint you with the Oyl of joy and gladneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45 7. <hi>Thou loveſt Righteouſneſs, and hateſt Wickedneſs,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:102520:51"/>therefore God, thy God hath anointed thee with the Oyl of gladneſs above thy fellows.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. When by your ſins and backſlidings you have loſt your comforts, humble your Souls for your ſins, and the Lord will reſtore your loſt comforts. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.18. <hi>I will reſtore comforts to him, and to his Mourners. Mat.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">IX. Keep up the belief and perſwaſion of Gods Love to your Souls through Chriſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the troubles that come upon your inward or outward man, for the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Gods love will fill your hearts with joy and gladneſs, and be a ground of everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Joy to your Souls. <hi>Act</hi> 2.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt make me full of joy with thy countenance.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.16. <hi>God even our Father which hath loved us and given us everlaſting Conſolation. Joh</hi> 13.1. <hi>Jeſus loves his own, and that to the end, even whilſt in a ſinful and troubleſome world.</hi> The knowledge of the love of God in Chriſt, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth abiding joy, and ſulneſs of joy. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.9, 11. <hi>As the Father hath loved me, ſo have I loved you — Theſe things have I ſpoken unto you, that my joy might remain in you, and that your joy might be full.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. How may ſuch as have gotten the knowledge of their intereſt in Chriſt, retain the knowledge and perſwaſion of their intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:102520:52"/>
                  <p>It is of great uſe in the Life of Faith, and the promoting our Spiritual comfort, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to get the knowledge of our intereſt in Chriſt, and his ſaving benefits, but alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this knowledge. And becauſe this is not eaſily done, I ſhall lay down ſome helps there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
                  <p>§. What are good grounds to lay claim to an intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. Underſtand, and be clear in your grounds, on which you lay claim to an intereſt in Chriſt, and Salvation by Chriſt, and ſee that they be ſolid, conſonant to the Scriptures, and ſuch as will hold and abide in an hour of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And if you ask, what are good and ſure grounds for claiming an intereſt in Chriſt? I anſwer.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The free and general offer of Chriſt and Salvation by Chriſt, made in the Goſpel to every one, that is willing to recieve. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. <hi>And whoſoever will, let him take the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life freely.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The teſtimony of our own Conſciences, that we do willingly, cordially, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accept of Chriſt, as God offers him to us in the Goſpel; Our Conſciences know what actings there are in our Souls, towards God and Chriſt, whether we chuſe the Lord for our God and Portion, and whether we accept of Chriſt for our Saviour and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or whether we refuſe and reject him.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:102520:52"/>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2. <hi>O my Soul, thou haſt ſaid unto the Lord, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u art my God. Lam.</hi> 3.24. <hi>The Lord is my portion ſaith my Soul—</hi> Now this Teſtimony of our Conſciences, that we do accept of Chriſt on the terms of the Goſpel, to be ruled and ſaved by him, in his own way, is a good ground of comfort, and may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden us to hope that God doth accept us in Chriſt. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Our rejoycing is this, the Teſtimony of our Conſcience.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 3.21. <hi>Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God.</hi> When I ſpeak of the Teſtimony of Conſcience witneſſing our accepting of Chriſt on the terms of the Goſpel, underſtand it of a Conſcience enlightned by the word and Spirit, with the knowledge of Chriſt. (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. <hi>I know whom I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi>) and the knowledge of the terms on which God offers Salvation by Chriſt, for if we know not the terms on which Chriſt is offered to us, how can our Conſciences wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us, that we do cloſe with the terms of the Goſpel.</item>
                     <item>3. The grant or promiſe of God in the Goſpel to all that recieve Chriſt, that he ſhall be theirs, and they ſhall be his. <hi>Joh</hi> 1.12. <hi>As many as recieved him, to them gave he power to become the Sons of God, even to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on his name.</hi> Here is a priviledge grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and promiſed to all that do or ſhall recieve Chriſt, how many ſoever they be, that they ſhall become the Sons of God, God will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:102520:53"/>their Father in Chriſt, and will own them for his children. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. <hi>Him that cometh unto me I will in no wiſe caſt him out.</hi> In this promiſe is implyed, that ſuch as on the call of the Goſpel cloſe with Chriſt, he will beſtow himſelf, and all his benefits on them for theirs, and he will own them for his.</item>
                     <item>4. Our finding in our ſelves, thoſe marks or characters, which the Scriptures give of ſuch as have a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, which will evidence to us, that we have rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieved or cloſed with Chriſt. As namely our having the Spirit of Chriſt given to us. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Hereby we know that we dwell in him, and he in us, becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit.</hi> Our loving and preſerving Chriſt above all things. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his.</hi> But of theſe Scripture characters I have ſpoken before.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>§. Chriſt becomes theirs by covenant that accept of him. How conduceth this to our comfort?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If you would hold the perſwaſion of your intereſt in Chriſt, as you muſt look to your grounds on which you lay claim to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, ſo alſo it will be of great uſe to you to underſtand the nature of that cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which Chriſt maketh with you, when you come to him and accept of him on the terms of the Goſpel. The Lord Jeſus takes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102520:53"/>all thoſe that come to him upon the call and invitation of the Goſpel, into an everlaſting covenant. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 3. <hi>Ho, every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters — Incline your ear, and come unto me—And I will make an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David.</hi> Concerning this covenant which the Lord maketh with thoſe that come to Chriſt, we may obſerve theſe three or four things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. This covenant is to give us Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all his ſaving benefits for ever, <hi>I will make an everlaſting Covenant with you, even the ſure Mercies of David.</hi> Chriſt the Son of <hi>David,</hi> is called by the name of <hi>David. Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.24. And ſo the ſure mercies of <hi>David,</hi> are all thoſe Mercies and Bleſſings which Jeſus Chriſt hath purchaſed for us, and made ſure to us by an everlaſting covenant, 'tis as much as to ſay, I will enter covenant to give you my ſelf, and all my benefits. That this covenant which Chriſt inters into, with thoſe that come to him, is to give us an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſt in himſelf, and all his benefits. We may ſee <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19, 20. <hi>I will betroth thee unto me for ever, yea, I will betroth thee unto me in Righteouſneſs, and in Judgment, and in Mercies, I will even betroth thee unto me in Faithfulneſs.</hi> To open this Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.
<list>
                           <item>1. What it is for the Lord to betroth us unto himſelf. It is to engage himſelf to us
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:102520:54"/>to be ours, and to take us for his.</item>
                           <item>2. For how long a time the Lord engageth himſelf to us, and that is for ever. <hi>I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth thee unto me for ever.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. The manner how he will betroth us to himſelf; <hi>in Righteouſneſs, in Judgment, in Mercies, in Faithfulneſs.</hi> It is a moſt ſure contract, made out of infinite mercy, and managed with Wiſdom, and Judgment, and ſhall be Righteouſly and Faithfully obſerved.</item>
                           <item>4. The perſons that the Lord will betroth to himſelf, are thoſe who are willing to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from their ſins, and to accept of Chriſt for their Husband— <hi>ver.</hi> 7.19. <hi>I will go and return to my firſt Huſband—I will betroth thee to me—</hi> They whom God taketh into Covenant with himſelf. <hi>ver.</hi> 18.19. <hi>I will make a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for them— And I will betroth thee to me for ever.</hi> And 'tis alſo to be obſerved, that the Lord repeats this three times— <hi>I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth thee, yea I will betroth thee, I will even betroth thee unto me,</hi> that we may reſt ſatisfied that our former ſins though great, ſhall not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us on our Repentance, from this great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of being betrothed to the Lord for ever. That the covenant is to give a mutual and eternal intereſt, that is, that the Lord will be ours for ever, and take us for his for ever, you may ſee. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.28. <hi>Yeſhallbe my people, and I will be your God. Pſal.</hi> 48.14. <hi>This God is our God for ever and for ever Lam.</hi> 3.31. <hi>The Lord will not caſt off for ever.</hi>
                              <pb n="99" facs="tcp:102520:54"/>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.22. <hi>The Lord will not forſake his People, for his great names ſake, becauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord to make you his people.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. This Covenant which the Lord Jeſus Chriſt maketh with us upon our coming to him, wherein he engageth to be ours, and to take us for his for ever, is a ſure, and everlaſting covenant; 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. More firm and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt than the Hills and Mountains, which ſhall all be removed out of their places, ſooner than Gods covenant ſhall be removed from us. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>For the Mountains ſhall depart, and the Hills ſhall be removed, but my kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee, nor the Covenant of my peace be removed ſaith the Lord, that hath Mercy on thee.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The failings and back-ſlidings of the Members of Chriſt, ſhall not make void this everlaſting covenant, he will chaſten them for their ſins and backſlidings, but he will not break his covenant with them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.30, 31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>If his Children forſake my Law, and walk not in my judgments, if they break my Statutes and keep not my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; then will I viſit their Tranſgreſſion with the rod, and their iniquity with ſtripes; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take from him, nor ſuffer my Faithfulneſs to fail. My Covenant will I not break, nor alter the thing that is gone out of my Lips.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:102520:55"/>
                  <p>§. No doubts, about our Spiritual eſtate, to be indulged, or admitted, but upon Scripture grounds.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. After you have cloſed with Chriſt, and God hath cleared up to your Souls your intereſt in Chriſt, by his Word and Spirit, admit no doubts about your intereſt in Chriſt, but upon Scripture grounds. Satan labours what he can, to keep us in a doubting condition, all our dayes; becauſe doubts of this nature, hinder our comfort, weaken our faith, and are impediments to our glorifying God: And therefore after cleareſt evidences of our intereſt in Chriſt, he will be thruſting doubts into our minds, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther webe Chriſts, yea, or no; that he may puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zleus herein as long as we live. After our Lord Jeſus Chriſt had it witneſſed to him from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that he was the Son of God. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17. <hi>And lo a voice from Heaven, ſaying, this is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> The Devil tempted him twice with doubts about his Sonſhip. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.3, 6. <hi>If thou be the Son of God — if thou be the Son of God.</hi> Now if Satan adventured to ſuggeſt doubts to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, after he had his Sonſhip witneſſed in an extraordinary manner, even by his Fathers voice, ſpeaking from Heaven to him, it is no marvail if he be often ſuggeſting doubts to us about our intereſt in Chriſt, after cleareſt manifeſtations thereof. Wherefore it will be our wiſdom to examine all our doubts, to ſee whether there be real grounds from the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102520:55"/>Holy Scriptures for ſuch doubts, and if there be not, then to reject them as the ſuggeſtions of Satan, and the ſinful fruit of our own unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, miſtruſtful hearts. As Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, Matth.</hi> 14.31. <hi>O thou of little faith, wherefore didſt thou doubt?</hi> So ſhould we ſay to our own hearts, when doubts ariſe in our hearts; wherefore do I doubt? Have I cauſe from the word of God, to queſtion my intereſt in Chriſt, becauſe of this, or that, which is ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to me? If not, reject thoſe doubts as cauſeleſs, and as proceeding from Satan.</p>
                  <p>§. Intereſt in Chriſt is conſiſtent with great imperfections, ſore afflictions, dreadful temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, conflicts between the Fleſh and Spirit, want of influences, ſucceſleſneſs in Holy Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the hideings of Gods face.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is of great uſe to the holding faſt the perſwaſion of our intereſt in Chriſt, to have a right underſtanding of the State and Condition of a Chriſtian in this preſent evil world. A man may be united unto Chriſt, and have a ſaving intereſt in him, and yet be ſenſible of many and great imperfections, and be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſharp afflictions, and dreadful temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; he may feel a law in his Members, warring againſt the law of his mind, and find great conflicts between the Fleſh, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; he may feel great dryneſs, and want of Spiritual influences, and be under the hideings of Gods face, and meet with other exerciſes of his Faith, and notwithſtanding all theſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:102520:56"/>things, he may be Chriſts, and Chriſt may be his. As I ſhall ſhew by inſtanceing in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. A man may be ſenſible of much imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in himſelf, he may find very great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in his beſt duties, and yet be one that hath a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, God may be his Father, and he may be one of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6, 8. <hi>We are all as an unclean thing, and our righteouſneſſes are as filthy rags— But now O Lord, thou art our Father.</hi> There are Babes in Chriſt, as well as young Men and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and they that are but Babes in Chriſt, are ſo full of imperfections, that in ſome things they ſeem more like to carnal men, than Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. <hi>And I brethren could not ſpeak unto you, as unto ſpiritual, but as unto carrnal, even as unto babes in Chriſt,</hi> yet theſe Babes in Chriſt, that had much carnality in them, were truly intereſted in Chriſt, as we may ſee, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>ye are Chriſts.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. A man may be exerciſed with ſharp and ſore afflictions, ſuch as may melt, and break his heart, and yet have a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.2, 16. <hi>As a Lilie among Thorns, ſo is my love among the Daughters — My beloved is mine, and I am his.</hi> When the Spouſe was a Lilie among Thorns, that is, compaſſed about with ſharp afflictions, which did prick, and grieve her like Thorns, ſhe was Chriſts Love, and Chriſt was hers, and ſhe was his. When <hi>David</hi> was afflicted very much, and his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102520:56"/>ſuch, as melted his Soul, and broke his heart, he did not queſtion his intereſt, becauſe of his afflictions, but could and did own it, that he was the Lords. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.28, 107. <hi>My Soul melteth for heavineſs — I am afflicted very much</hi>—compared with <hi>ver.</hi> 94. <hi>I am thine, ſave me.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>A man may be exerciſed with horrid and dreadful temptations, and yet be one that hath an intereſt in Chriſt. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a choſen Veſſel, and had an undoubted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt; was under the buffettings of Satan, which were as grievous to his Soul, as a Thorn is grievous to the Fleſh. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. <hi>There was given to me a Thorn in the Fleſh, the Meſſenger of Satan to buffet me, leſt I ſhould be exalted above meaſure.</hi> Our Lord Jeſus himſelf, was tempted by Satan to great, and grievous ſins, to get bread when he was hungry, to caſt down himſelf from a Pinacle of the Temple, which was in effect to have deſtroyed himſelf, and to fall down, and worſhip the Devil. And what worſe ſin than to worſhip the Devil? <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.6, 9. Now if Satan adventured to tempt our Lord Jeſus Chriſt to ſuch horrid ſins as theſe are; We need not wonder if he aſſault his Members with temptations to the worſt of ſins, as Blaſphemy, Idolatry, Atheiſm, Self-Murder, and the like.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A man may have a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, and yet feel in himſelf the indwelling corruption, which may incline him to that which is evil, and hinder him in doing that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:102520:57"/>good, which he deſireth to do. He may feel the luſtings of the Fleſh, oppoſing the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Spirit of Grace: He may feel the Law in his Members, warring againſt the Law of his Mind, and ſometimes leading him Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the Law of Sin, and yet be one that is made a partaker of the ſaving benefits of Chriſt. We find the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> uttering ſuch complaints as theſe. <hi>Sin dwelleth in me— The good that I would, that I do not, but the evil which I would not, that I do — I find a Law, that when I would do good, evil is preſent with me. I ſee another Law in my Members, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the Law of my mind, and bringing me into Captivity, to the Law of ſin which is in my Members. Rom.</hi> 7.17, 19, 21, 23. Yet at the ſame time that he uttered theſe complaints, he did look upon himſelf to be Chriſts, and did bleſs God for his intereſt in Chriſt, and the benefits he had by Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>I thank God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> The <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> felt in themſelves the luſtings of the Fleſh againſt the Spirit, whereby they were hindred in well-doing. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>The Fleſh lusteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the Fleſh, and theſe are contrary, the one to the other, ſo that ye cannot do the things that ye would.</hi> Yet theſe Perſons, that felt theſe conflicts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Fleſh and the Spirit, were the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God through Faith in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 26. <hi>Ye are all the Children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:102520:57"/>
                  <p n="5">5. A man may be ſenſible of much dryneſs, and be under a great want of the influences of the Spirit of Grace, and yet he may have a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, and God may be his God and Father in Chriſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.83, 94. <hi>I am become like a bottle in the ſmoke — I am thine, ſave me</hi> — When the Pſalmiſt found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf like a bottle in the ſmoke, that is in a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, drie, parched condition, he did, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his drie and withered condition, believe himſelf to be the Lords — <hi>I am thine, ſave me.</hi> So alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.4, 7. <hi>My moiſture is turned into the drought of Summer — Thou art my hiding place.</hi> He did believe his intereſt in God, though he found himſelf in ſuch a dry condition, that he complained his moiſture was turned into the drought of Summer, that is, was ſo gone, as he could not diſcern any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in him. An example of believing God to be our Father, in, and through Chriſt, under a ſuſpenſion of influencees, we have <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.15, 16. <hi>VVhere is thy zeal and thy ſtrength, and the ſounding of thy bowels, and of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies towards me, are they reſtrained! Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou art our Father — Thou O Lord art our Father, our Redeemer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. A man may be under the withdrawings of God, the Lord may hide his face from him, and though he ſeek the Lord, he may give no anſwers to his Prayers, and yet God may be his Father in Chriſt, and he may have a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.7, 8. <hi>Thou
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:102520:58"/>haſt hid thy face from us—But now O Lord, thou art our Father. Cant.</hi> 2.16. Compared with <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.6. <hi>My beloved is mine. and I am his— I opened to my beloved, but my beloved had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf, and was gone — I ſought him, but I could not find him, I called him, but He gave me no anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. A man may be ſucceſleſs in Holy Duties, he may not find what his Soul ſeeks after in Gods Ordinances, and yet Chriſts may be his, and he may be Chriſts. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1. <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his. By night on my bed, I ſought him whom my Soul loveth, I ſought him, but I found him not.</hi> Here is earneſtneſs, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in ſeeking Chriſt, <hi>I ſought him, I ſought him,</hi> it's mentioned twice. Here is ſincerity in ſeeking Chriſt, a ſeeking him out of love, and yet no ſucceſs, <hi>but I found him not. Iſa.</hi> 49.4. <hi>I have laboured in vain, and ſpent my ſtrength for nought, yet ſurely my judgment is with the Lord, and my work with my God.</hi> Here is labour in vain as to men, and a ſpending our ſtrength for nought, and yet a claiming an intereſt in God.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. A man that hath a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, may be under various and different tempers, and frames of Spirit. He may have his Ups, and his Downs, ſometimes his heart may be in a raiſed elevated frame, he may have ſuch an high meaſure of Faith, as to fear nothing. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Behold God is my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I will truſt, and not be afraid. Pſ.</hi> 27.1.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:102520:58"/>
                     <hi>The Lord is my Light and Salvation, whom ſhall I fear!</hi> At another time the ſame perſon may be in a very low and dejected frame, that his Soul may as it were cleave to the duſt. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.26. <hi>My ſoul cleaveth to the Duſt. Pſal.</hi> 42.6. <hi>O my God, my Soul is caſt down within me.</hi> At one time he may have ſweet peace and comfort, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 94.19. <hi>Thy comforts delight my Soul.</hi> Another time he may be in a diſturbed, diſquieted frame, and go mourning all the day long. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 42.11. <hi>VVhy art thou caſt down O my Soul, and why art thou diſquieted within me; Pſ.</hi> 38.6. <hi>I am troubled, I am bowed down greatly, I go mourning all the day long.</hi> At one time he may be in a lively frame, and have earneſt longings and breathings after God. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 42.1, 2. <hi>As the heart panteth after the water-brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee O God. My Soul thirſteth for God—</hi> At another time he may be in a dead, dull, and ſtupid frame, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.22. <hi>I was as a beaſt before thee. Pſ.</hi> 143.3, 4. <hi>He hath made me to dwell in darkneſs, as thoſe that have been long dead— My heart within me is deſolate. Pſ.</hi> 102.4. <hi>My heart is ſmitten, and withered like graſs.</hi> At one time he may be in a melting broken frame, at another time in ſuch an hardned frame, that he may wonder to ſee how hard his heart is. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16, 17. <hi>Doubtleſs thou art our Father— O Lord why haſt thou made us to err from thy wayes, and hardned our hearts from thy fear.</hi> At one time he may walk in the light of Gods
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:102520:59"/>countenance. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.6. <hi>Thou haſt made him exceeding glad with thy countenance.</hi> At ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time he may be under the hidings of Gods face, and that for ſo long a time, as to fear that God will never return to him again. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 13.1. <hi>How long wilt thou forget me, (O Lord) for ever? How long wilt thou hide thy face from me?</hi> Thus we ſee how the Children of God are liable to variety of changes in their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſtate, and in the frame of their hearts, only let this be added alſo, when ever their hearts are out of frame, they are unquiet and troubled, and can't be at reſt till they get into a good frame again. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.7. <hi>Thou didſt hide thy face and I was troubled.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. A man may be in a very dark and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed condition, and want the preſence of God, and think himſelf forſaken of God, and yet be one that hath a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. <hi>Who is there among you that feareth the Lord—that walketh in darkneſs, and ſeeth no Light—let him ſtay himſelf upon his God.</hi> The Lord is his God that heareth him, though he walk in darkneſs, and can't apprehend it. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.17. <hi>It was now dark, and Jeſus was not come to them.</hi> They were Chriſts own Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that wanted Chriſts preſence when they were at Sea, in a dark night, when there was a great Tempeſt that endangered their Lives. See alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14, 15, 16.</p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:102520:59"/>
                  <p>§. It is a great help to hold in our intereſt in Chriſt, to commune often with our own hearts about our Spiritual eſtate.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Another help to the holding the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our intereſt in Chriſt, is to commune often with our own hearts, about our Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſtate, and the grounds of our claiming an intereſt in Chriſt, and our performance of thoſe terms which the Goſpel propoſeth in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our enjoying the ſaving benefits of Chriſt, as namely whether we do indeed believe on him, and repent of our ſins, and obey Chriſt as our Lord, and love and prefer him above all things, and deny our ſelves, and take up our Croſs, and follow him. For
<list>
                        <item>1. The oftner we ſearch our ſelves, and commune with our own hearts, the clearer Knowledge we ſhall have of our Spiritual ſtate. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Examine your ſelves whether ye be in the Faith, know ye not your own ſelves how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you.</hi> If we be doubtful and deſirous to know whether Chriſt be in us, the way to come unto this knowledge is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our ſelves, whether we be in the Faith. What the Pſalmiſt ſaith of Gods ſearching him; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.1. <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſearched me, and known me.</hi> The ſame is true of ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves, by ſearching our ſelves we ſhall know our ſelves. As <hi>Solomon</hi> by communing with his own heart, grew in Wiſdom and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.16. <hi>I communed with mine own heart— Yea my heart had great Experience
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:102520:60"/>of Wiſdom and Knowledge;</hi> So ſhall we have great experience and knowledge of our hearts, if we do often commune with them.</item>
                        <item>2. While we are communing with our own hearts about our Spiritual Eſtate, it pleaſeth the Lord oft times to draw War to us, and to illuminate our minds, and to evidence to us the Graces that are wrought in us. As it fared with the two Diſciples. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.15. <hi>And it came to paſs, that while they communed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and reaſoned, Jeſus himſelf drew near, and went with them.</hi> So it often comes to paſs with the Children of God, whilſt they are Communing and Reaſoning with their own hearts, that Jeſus Chriſt draws near to them with his Holy Spirit, and ſealeth up Inſtruction to them. And as it was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he turned aſide to ſee and conſider that great work of God, a Buſh burning and not conſumed, when the Lord ſaw that he turned aſide to ſee the work of God. God ſpake to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and revealed himſelf to him. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.3, 4, 6. So 'tis here, when we turn aſide from our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affairs to commune with our own hearts, about the workings of Gods grace upon our Souls, he reveals and diſcovers to us our cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant intereſt in himſelf.</item>
                        <item>3. Communing with our own hearts, and recollecting former experiences of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious dealings with us, will ſtill thoſe troubled thoughts which ariſe in our minds about our Spiritual and Eternal State. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102520:60"/>with your own heart upon your Bed, and be still.</hi> When the Pſalmiſt was in a troubled condition, and had many ſad thoughts, as if God would caſt him off for ever, and ſhew him no Mercy, he was quieted when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muned with his own heart, and recollected Gods gracious dealings with him in former days. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</item>
                        <item>4. Frequent communing with our own hearts, will diſcover our irregular walkings, and put us upon returning to God after we have gone aſtray; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59. <hi>I thought on my wayes, and turned my Feet unto thy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi> And turning to God, and walking in his ways, will preſerve our peace, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Spirit of Adoption in us. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt call me my Father, and ſhall not turn away.</hi> If we would call God our Father, we muſt be careful we do not turn away from the Lord.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>§. Get Scruples reſolved.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. See what are your moſt material doubts and ſcruples, which make you call in queſtion your Intereſt in Chriſt, and beg of God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve thoſe doubts, and remove thoſe ſcruples, and obſerve what Reſolution God gives you by his Word and Spirit, after you ſought to him by Prayer. For after Prayer God is wont to give us intimation of our Intereſt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Son, and to give us boldneſs to claim our intereſt in him. <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.9. <hi>They
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:102520:61"/>ſhall call and I will hear them, I will ſay, it is my people, and they ſhall ſay, the Lord is my God.</hi> Such intimations of our Intereſt in God and Chriſt, and ſuch encouragements to claim Intereſt in God as are given in after Prayer, are to be carefully obſerved and recorded ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for they may be of great uſe to us; what was ſaid in the fourth direction about the ſtate of a Chriſtian in this preſent evil world, may be of great uſe to the reſolving ſcruples about our Intereſt in Chriſt. And alſo what is added after the uſe of Examination.</p>
                  <p>§. What to do when we can't get our doubts and ſcruples anſwered.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. When your doubts and ſcruples, and darkneſs are of that nature, that you can't come to a Reſolution about your intereſt in Chriſt, cloſe a new with Jeſus Chriſt. Seeing your ſelves under the offer of Chriſt in the goſpel, ſay thus within your ſelves, though I can't make out that Chriſt is mine, I ſee God offers him freely to me, and therefore I will now accept of him that he may be mine; and I do and will in a ſolemn manner engage my ſelf to him to be his. This will cut thoſe knots in ſunder which we can't untie. And a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent renewal of our choice of Chriſt for our Lord and Saviour, our renewed acceptance of him upon the terms of the Goſpel, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation and judgment, and ſolemn ſurrendring our ſelves to Chriſt to be his,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:102520:61"/>would tend much to the clearing our intereſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.30, 94. <hi>I have choſen the way of truth—I am thine. David</hi> who had choſen God to be his God, and the ways of God to be the ways that he would walk in, could with an holy boldneſs ſay unto God, <hi>I am thine, ſave me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>§. An Holy Converſation is a means to preſerve the Aſſurance of our Intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. If we would retain the perſwaſion of our Intereſt in Chriſt, we muſt be careful to order our Converſations aright, and walk as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, for an Holy Converſation is a ſpecial means to obtain the aſſurance of our Salvation. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. <hi>To him that ordereth his Converſation aright, will I ſhew the Salvation of God. Iſa.</hi> 32.17. <hi>The work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the effect of Righteouſneſs, quietneſs and aſſurance for ever.</hi> I might inſtance here in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular branches of Righteouſneſs, which tend to the breeding and preſerving of an aſſurance of our being in a ſtate of Grace and Salvation; as walking in Love, and being ready to do all offices of Love one for another. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18.19. <hi>My little Children, let us not love in Word or in Tongue, but in Deed and in Truth. And hereby we know that we are of the Truth, and ſhall aſſure our hearts before him.</hi> This is the way, not only to get aſſurance, but to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:102520:62"/>keep it to the end of our days, to ſhew our love in our diligence, in Miniſtring to the Saints as we have ability, and as their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty requireth. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10, 11. Another Grace that will much further our Aſſurance, as truſting in God in all diſtreſſes and dangers, and living by Faith on Gods promiſes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.14. <hi>I truſted in thee, I ſaid thou art my God.</hi> The more we accuſtom our ſelves to truſt in God, the more confidently we ſhall be enabled to call God our God. Another grace that will further our aſſurance is Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; when we walk in our Integrity, that will ſcatter and diſpel fears, and bring in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.4. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright there ariſeth Light in Darkneſs.</hi> But I ſhall add no more upon this queſtion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. What they ſhould do, that can't make out their intereſt in Chriſt, in a time of trouble, and at the hour of Death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> It may be ſome will ſay, it is true, they that have an intereſt in Chriſt, and know it may be of good chear under all the troubles of this Life, and when they are to paſs through the Valley of the Shadow of Death, but what ſhall I do in an evil day, and at the hour of Death, that cannot to this day, nor ever could make it out that I have a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:102520:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>§. Prayer a means to clear intereſt. Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to pray for this mercy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Pray to God to make clear, to your Souls, your intereſt in himſelf, and his Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.3. <hi>Say unto my Soul I am thy Salvation.</hi> That which <hi>David</hi> asks is not, be thou my Salvation, but 'tis the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his Soul with the knowledge that God was his Saviour, and would give him Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Say unto my Soul</hi>— That is, Lord per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my Soul, Lord give my Soul ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this great caſe, that thou art my Saviour, and wilt confer Salvation upon me. And what <hi>David</hi> prayed for in this kind, that may we pray for alſo. And for our encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to pray for the knowledge of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, conſider theſe things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Prayer is a means of Gods own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not only for the obtaining of the favour of God, but alſo for the obtaining of the comfortable apprehenſions of Gods love in Chriſt. <hi>Job.</hi> 33.26. <hi>He ſhall pray unto God, and he ſhall be favourable unto him, and he ſhall ſee his face with joy.</hi> Here is a double bleſſing promiſed unto the man that prayeth unto God, he ſhall obtain the favour of God, and he ſhall ſee his face with joy, that is, he ſhall obtain the knowledge of Gods love to his Soul, which ſhall put great joy and gladneſs into his heart.</item>
                     <item>2. The knowledge of our intereſt in God
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:102520:63"/>as our Father, and in Chriſt as our Saviour and Redeemer, is promiſed in the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; and what the Lord hath promiſed, we may pray in Faith and Hope that we ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it. See promiſes to this purpoſe; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt know that I the Lord am thy Saviour, and thy Redeemer.</hi> That which is here promiſed, is not, I will be thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, but the knowledge of our intereſt in Chriſt as our Saviour, and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. It is not ſaid, thou ſhalt know that I am the Saviour of <hi>my people,</hi> or the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of <hi>thoſe that truſt in me, Thon ſhalt know that I the Lord am thy Saviour, and thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</hi> Another promiſe of clearing our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, we have, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20. <hi>At that day ye ſhall know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you.</hi> At that day, what day is here meant? ſome underſtand it of the future life, when we ſhall live with Chriſt in Glory, ſpoken of in the foregoing verſe, <hi>becauſe I live, ye ſhall live alſo, at that day ye ſhall know</hi>— And doubtleſs the full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of this promiſe is the priviledge of the other life, to have a perfect underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the myſtical Union, between the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, and between Chriſt and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. But it hath alſo a reſpect to clearing our Union with Chriſt in this life; at that day, that is after I am riſen from the dead, and gone to the Father, and at that day, that you ſet your love upon me, and keep my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:102520:63"/>and I ſhall pray the Father, and he ſhall ſend you another comforter, even the Spirit of truth, he ſhall make it known to you, that I am in you, and you in me. It may alſo relate to <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 14. When you ſhall earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray to the Father in my name, to have your union cleared, in that day you ſhall know that I am in you, and you in me. If any ſay, I have prayed to God to clear my Union with, and my Intereſt in Chriſt, and ſtill I am in the dark about this matter. I anſwer, You muſt continue to ſeek this mercy, the knowledge of your intereſt in God and Chriſt, and that is the way to obtain it. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord</hi>—</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>§. Such as can't make out their Intereſt in Chriſt, ſhould cloſe with Chriſt, that they may have an Intereſt in him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If you cant, nor ever could make out your Intereſt in Chriſt, yea, ſuppoſe it be ſo that you have no intereſt in him, come in now, and cloſe with him. The door of Hope ſtill ſtands open to your Souls. It is yet an accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time, and a day of Salvation. God ſtill continueth to offer Chriſt to your Souls, and prays you to accept of him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>VVe pray you in Chriſts ſtead, be you reconciled to God.</hi> If at length, after a long neglecting of Chriſt, you will come in, and cloſe with him, you ſhall be ſaved by him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.7. <hi>To day, after ſo long a time, as it is ſaid, to day if you
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:102520:64"/>will bear his voice, harden not your hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe that had ſtood all the day idle, even to the laſt hour, were invited to go into the Vineyard, and going upon the invitation, had their reward. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.6, 7, 9. <hi>And about the eleventh hour, he went out, and found others ſtanding idle, and ſaith unto them, why ſtand ye here all the day idle — Go ye alſo into the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and whatever is right, that ſhall ye receive. And when they came that were hired about the eleventh hour, they received every man a penny.</hi> This penny is by the generality of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters agreed to be eternal life, and this eternal life ſhall be given to thoſe that come into Chriſt at the laſt hour of the day, though the former part of their time hath been ſpent in ideleneſs. But ſome may ſay, if a man hath reflected, and lived without God in the day of his proſperity, is there hope if ſuch a man turn to God in the day of trouble, that God will be found of him, and be gracious unto him: I anſwer: There is hope for ſuch as have neglected God along time, if they turn to him in the day of their tròuble, that he will be gracious unto them. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.3, 4. <hi>Now for a long ſeaſon, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael hath been without the true God — But when they in their trouble did turn unto the Lord God of Iſrael, he was found of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>§. Such as want Evidence of their intereſt in Chriſt, ought to truſt in him for Salvation. What grounds have ſuch to truſt in Chriſt?</p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:102520:64"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Though you want evidence of your intereſt in Chriſt, in a time of trouble, and at the hour of Death; yet if you be ſuch as live in the fear of God, ſuch as deſire to be ſaved by Chriſt in his own way, and upon his own Terms, you may, yea, you ought to truſt in Chriſt for eternal Salvation. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. <hi>VVho is among you that fears the Lord, that obeyeth the voice of his Servants, that walketh in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and hath no light, let him trust in the name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his God.</hi> A man that truly feareth God, may be in great darkneſs about his Spiritual State, he may have no light, that is, no Evidence of his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in God, and the promiſes, and ſo be in a very uncomfortable condition, yet ſuch ought to truſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>If any ſay, what grounds hath a man that followeth after Righteouſneſs, and deſireth to live in the fear of God, and yet wanteth evidence of his Intereſt in Chriſt, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, to truſt in Chriſt for his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
                  <p>§. Grounds of truſting in Chriſt for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſuch as are in a dark condition, as to their Intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. God ſends his Son into the World, to take our nature upon him, and to die for our Sins for this very end and purpoſe, to ſeek and to ſave Sinners, who were in a loſt, and undone condition. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>This is a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:102520:65"/>faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of whom I am chief. Luk.</hi> 19.10. <hi>The Son of man is come to ſeek, and to ſave that which is loſt.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.14. <hi>VVe have ſeen, and do teſtifie that the Father ſent the Son to be the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the VVorld. John</hi> 3.17. <hi>God ſent not his Son into the world to condemn the world, but that the world through him might be ſaved.</hi> Theſe general expreſſions to ſave the World, to ſave Sinners, to ſave that which was loſt, opens a door of hope to ſuch as can't ſee their intereſt in Chriſt, but ſee themſelves loſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and hearing that the Father ſent his Son to be the Saviour of the world, to ſave loſt ſinners, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhews them that there is hope for their Souls, that they may obtain Salvation By Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world, and who came into the world purpoſely to ſave ſinners, is an all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Saviour, able to ſave unto the uttermoſt all that come unto God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>He is able to ſave them unto the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, ſeeing He ever liveth to make interceſſion for them.</hi> He is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, that is to ſave perfectly, to ſave eternally, to give all things requiſite to Salvation, he is able to juſtifie, ſanctifie, and bring unto glory all that come unto him. For his blood is available to take away the greateſt ſins of the greateſt ſinners in the whole world.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:102520:65"/>
                     <hi>John</hi> 1.29. <hi>Behold the Lamb of God that tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away the ſin of the world.</hi> And his Spirit is able to ſanctifie the worſt and moſt polluted Sinners. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> were the chief of Sinners, Extortioners, Drunkards, Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Abuſers of themſelves with mankind, with other abominations; yet they were ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the Spirit of Chriſt, of great ſinners made eminent Saints. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 62.10, 11.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt inviteth, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all diſtreſſed Perſons in all places, that ſee themſelves in a periſhing undone condition, to look to him, and to come to him for Salvation. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. <hi>Look unto me, and be ye ſaved all the ends of Earth.</hi> That is, let all Perſons from one end of the Earth to the other, that find a want of Salvation, look unto me, and I will ſave them. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Lord commandeth us to truſt in his Son for the giving us eternall life. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.23. <hi>This is his Commandment that we ſhould believe on the name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and love one another as he gave us Commandment.</hi> And he is diſpleaſed with thoſe that do not relie on him for their Salvation. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.21, 22. <hi>The Lord was wroth — and anger came up againſt Iſrael, becauſe they believed not in God, and truſted not in his Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. We have God promiſes, yea, many promiſes, that he will give eternal life, and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:102520:66"/>bleſſedneſs to all, whoſoever they be that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and truſt in his Son, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him. Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life. Joh.</hi> 6.47. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, He that believeth on me, hath everlaſting life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>§. The plea of ſuch as can't truſt in Chriſt for Salvation, for want of Sanctification.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. None ſhall be ſaved by Chriſt, but ſuch as are ſanctified, and in a ſtate of Grace, but I want evidences of my being ſanctified, and being in a ſtate of Grace, how then can I truſt in Chriſt to ſave me?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. It is true, that Chriſt ſanctifieth all whom he ſaveth, for without Holineſs, no man whatſoever ſhall ſee the Lord. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Follow peace with all men, and holineſs, without which, no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> If a man live and dye in his ſins without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and yet truſt in Chriſt for Salvation, he doth but delude himſelf; for our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus telleth us expreſly, that all that do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, ſhall ſurely periſh. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3. <hi>I tell you nay, but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though you want evidences of your
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:102520:66"/>Sanctification, yet, do you not find ardent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of Sanctification; do you not find hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grings and thirſtings after Righteouſneſs? Such as hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs, are in a bleſſed condition, as well as they that have attained Righteouſneſs. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs, for they ſhall be filled.</hi> Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al deſires are an argument of the Grace of God beſtowed upon us. The gracious eſtate of the Servants of God is ſometimes ſet out by their deſires. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.8. <hi>The deſire of our Souls is to thee, and to the remembrance of thy name. Neh.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Thy Servants who deſire to fear thy name</hi> — Then our deſires argue a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtate, when our deſires of God, and the things of God exceed our deſires of other things. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.25. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, and there is none on Earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. If you find in your ſelf a want of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, know this, that you are to truſt in Chriſt for Sanctification, as well as Salvation. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us Sanctification.</hi> Now if Chriſt be made of God unto us Sanctification, then we may, we ought to truſt in Chriſt for Sanctification, as well as other Bleſſings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> laſt. Learn hence, that they which have gotten their intereſt in Chriſt cleared to their
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:102520:67"/>Souls need not to be afraid of death, but may depart in peace: A confirmation hereof we have in the example of this our deceaſed Siſter, Mrs. <hi>Ellen Aſty,</hi> who was a Mother in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who was ſo much above the fear of Death, that when I was with her, a few days before ſhe dyed, ſhe uſed theſe expreſſions. <hi>I can chearfully embrace death, I ſhould not be afraid of death, if I ſhould ſee him coming in at the Windows, if I ſhould ſee him come into my Chamber, for my beloved is mine, and I am his, and therefore ſhe knew he would not condemn her.</hi> And having found abundance of comfort in her intereſt in Chriſt, ſhe was deſirous that this Text might be Preached on at her Funeral, <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his,</hi> (I ſuppoſe) that others might be ſtirred up to get an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, and to get their intereſt made out. Several things have been obſerved, wherein ſhe may be exemplary to others, as may be ſeen in the account of her life, which followeth.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:67"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:68"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:68"/>
                  <p>THE LIFE OF Mrs. <hi>Ellen Aſty,</hi> THE Late Wife of Mr. <hi>Aſty</hi> of <hi>Stratford</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Revel. 14.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Bleſſed are the Dead that dye in the Lord.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> 1681.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:69"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102520:69"/>
                  <head>THE LIFE OF Mrs. <hi>Ellen Aſty,</hi> THE Wife of Mr. <hi>Aſty,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is exceedingly pleaſant unto many, to be beholding the Pictures of their deareſt Friends, when their perſons are removed out of their ſight, and laid in the ſilent duſt, and it hath been found more than a little profitable unto ſurviving Friends, to be reading over the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102520:70"/>lives of the moſt eminent Saints departed, as hereby being dead, they yet ſpeak, and become ſtill as living patterns for their imitation. It is ſaid, <hi>The memory of the juſt is Bleſſed. Prov.</hi> 10.7. And it may be ſaid of this pious Matron, as of <hi>Demetrius.</hi> 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. <hi>She hath a good report of all men, and of the truth it ſelf.</hi> As to her Birth and Education, much might be ſpoken. She was the Daughter of Mr. and Mrs. <hi>Bently,</hi> her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an eminent Godly Miniſter, her Mother a very Gracious, Holy Gentlewoman, who lived at <hi>Plumſted</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> who brought her up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord. She <hi>remembred her Creator in the days of her youth,</hi> and choſe him to be hers betimes. The Lord was pleaſed to begin a work of Grace ſo early upon her heart, and ripen it ſo faſt, that whilſt ſhe was young, and Nature not grown to its perfection, ſhe was a well grown Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in gracious experiences, excelling many who ſet out for Jeſus Chriſt long before her: that ſhe became a pattern of piety to others: yea, the whole Family where ſhe lived, before ſhe entred into a married eſtate, and many out of it, (even ſuch as occaſionally came into it) were much the better for her, and Bleſſed God that they had acquaintance with her, valuing her Grace and Judgment in the deep matters of the Goſpel. She was the wife of Mr. <hi>Aſty,</hi> a labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Miniſter of the Goſpel, whom God made much uſe of in the Converſion of many ſinners, and building up others in Grace and Holineſs,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102520:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>who were already brought home to Jeſus Chriſt. When ſhe was firſt married, ſeveral Gentlewomen ſent their Daughters to be with her, that they might live under her inſtructions, and the Lord made her very uſeful to them.</p>
                  <p>She was eminent for her deportment, and carriage in all Relations: ſome who had inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate acquaintance with her, do teſtify, that ſhe was dutiful to her Parents, an obedient and loving Wife to her Husband, a tender hearted Mother to her Children, (one ſaid) never did any bear the Souls of her Children, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Children, more upon their hearts than ſhe did; never was any more concerned for their Souls, nor did more Travel in Birth, than ſhe, till ſhe could ſee that in Chriſt they were born again; never any more concerned for the Souls of thoſe committed to her charge (though but ſervants,) than ſhe was.</p>
                  <p>Some Miniſters, and others who knew her Converſation, teſtifie of her gracious carriage and behaviour, in her various conditions, in the courſe of her Life, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>She was <hi>very knowing in the things of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and her knowledge was experimental, growing, humbling, and practical, a well grounded Profeſſor, and an honour and glory to her Profeſſion.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102520:71"/>
                  <p>She had a ſound Judgment, a well enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned underſtanding, in the myſtery of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>She had the Scriptures (the Fountain of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge) in very high eſtimation, and daily to the laſt, diligently ſearched into them, not one day paſſed but ſhe read, or had read to her, ſome portions of them, which ſhe made matter of meditation, and when her weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were ſo great, and her eyes ſo fail'd in the latter part of her life, that ſhe could not read her ſelf, ſhe called one to read to her, weighed all her actions by the Scriptures as her Rule, conſidered her warrant, call and command from God, for all ſhe did, and acted in all, in obedience thereunto.</p>
                  <p>She would often be telling others, how in their way they might ſerve the Lord, though the work of their place was never ſo mean and low, if they did conſider the precepts and rules, which God had given referring to ſuch a Relation, place, employ, or condition wherein they ſtood, and acted in obedience to his will therein.</p>
                  <p>She outwent moſt Chriſtians in <hi>her ſtrictneſs on the Lords day,</hi> the whole time was ſpent in publick and private exerciſes, and would allow nothing that was ſecular and aliene to Religion to be done in her Family, that was not of indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102520:71"/>neceſſity on that day, and always had a more than ordinary preparation in her houſe the day before, that thoſe in her family might have no temptation in that reſpect, to violate any part of the ſacred time of that day.</p>
                  <p>She was very exact as to her words, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes on that day, not opening her Lips to ſpeak any thing that wasnot ſuitable and agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the holineſs of that day, and it was a great burthen and affliction to her Spirit, which ſhe could not bear, but mourned under, to hear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers give their tongues a liberty to ſpeak any thing unſuitable and heterogeneal to the day, ſhe did <hi>highly prize all the ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> they were <hi>ſweeter to her than the hony, or the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Comb;</hi> more deſirable than her appointed food, never ſo much in her element as when waiting upon the Lord, either in publick or private opportunities, and to the laſt would venture through all difficulties, and bear up under great weakneſſes, in duties of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Communion, and could not live without them; her love to them and delight in them, was as ſtrong and freſh in her old age, as in the day of her Eſpouſals, when ſhe firſt ſet out, and began to taſt that the Lord was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. It is not to be ſpoken how ſhe hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her weak body to hear Sermons, to attend upon the Lord in all opportunities enjoyable. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t was generally obſerved in <hi>Stratford,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he was ſick indeed, if ſhe was not at the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102520:72"/>word; either on the Lords day, or at Church meetings on the week day. Nothing but a very afflictive hand of God kept her at home. It was her daily ſtudy how to glorifie God in every condition, and under every diſpenſation, that was either proſperous or adverſe, that was principally her ſtudy, how and in what way God might be moſt honoured, and his name advanced by her.</p>
                  <p>She had <hi>a heart for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Obedience,</hi> walking as <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Ordinances of the Lord, blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. She evidenced that ſhe was a friend to Jeſus Chriſt by doing whatever he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her, and through that friendſhip between Chriſt and her, ſhe found ſhe could do nothing ſo well as the will of Chriſt, and found that obedience eaſie; loved Jeſus Chriſt with a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative love, and ſerved him not with half an a heart, but ſincerely with the whole heart, yea delighted in ſerving of him, ſhe had a Law within, ſuitable to the Law without, which rendred it natural to her, to act graciouſly; Jeſus Chriſt was her Life, his Grace and Image were implanted in her Soul, that from a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of love to him, even in old age, when weak and ſickly, ſhe acted for Chriſt yea above her ſtrength, he was in her ſo much by his Spirit, that ſhe thought nothing too much to do for him and his. She was <hi>full of good projects and deſigns for Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> loved to viſit the ſick
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102520:72"/>and afflicted, and thoſe who walked in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as to their ſpiritual conditions, loved to acquaint themſelves with her; who by <hi>a great treaſure of experiences, was able to afford Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and comfort to them.</hi> A Chriſtian able to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon, to the relief of any ſoul under ſpiritual burdens and preſſures; And as ready to impart what Jeſus Chriſt had Communicated unto her, and the Lord Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated the more to her, becauſe ſhe was ſo free to Communicate to others, laying up her experiences as for her own good, ſo for others, that they might be comforted with the ſame comforts, that ſhe was comforted with-all. Her diſcourſe never tended to ſelf ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe or commendation, neither was it bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome, frothy or unſuitable, but always ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury Chriſtian and profitable, commanding the ears of all about her; In her Family ſhe was frequently taking opportunities in the day time and evening, and when ever ſhe thought it ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, to be ſpeaking of the things of God of the excellency of Jeſus Chriſt; of the way of Life by him; opening the miſerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſoul out of Jeſus Chriſt, ſetting forth the evil of ſin, the immortality of the Soul, the ſufferings and eternity of the puniſhment of Hell, to her Children, Servants, and thoſe that lived with her, and was daily dropping in and working upon them, to make them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and conſiderate, and as God had given her a choice gift that way, ſo he made a great
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102520:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>uſe thereof; her counſels, warnings, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, invitations, and holy inſtructions were made ſingularly advantagious and uſeful, to the convincing, quickning and edifying thoſe committed to her charge, ſo as they had cauſe for ever to bleſs God for the gracious words which proceeded out of her mouth.</p>
                  <p>She was always taking of opportunities, to be calling upon thoſe in a natural eſtate, to mind the great concerns of their Souls, and to be exciting, provoking, encouraging and ſtrengthning thoſe, whoſe face was Zion ward, her words were as choice Silver, ſeaſoned with Grace, moſtly Scriptural.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sermons that ſhe heard</hi> on the Lords day, or Week day, were much the Subject matter of her diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>The Light of Goſpel Grace and Truth did ſo ſhine in her, as that her preſence laid a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon Sinners, it was a curb unto vain Perſons, if they came into the Room where ſhe was preſent.</p>
                  <p>She was exact, and much in private Duties every day, and yet ſo prudent in the ſingling out of the time, as that the place in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wherein ſhe ſtood, never miſſed her. She had at all times a due reſpect to the duties of both Tables; and both in her Life
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102520:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Diſcourſes, ſhewed how inſeparable they were, commending to all perſons with whom ſhe had to do, the neceſſary and indiſpenſible obſervation of both: She looked upon time as a precious thing that was not to run waſte, and was diligent in the improvement of the Sands of every hour, ſo as there was no part of her Life from Morning unto Evening, that was an empty ſpace; but was laid out <hi>either in doing, or recieving good.</hi> Like the Summer ſhe brought forth every thing in its ſeaſon, wiſely forecaſting, and timeing whatſoever ſhe had the ordering of.</p>
                  <p>She ſtudied to excel in faithfulneſs and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righ neſs in all ſhe undertook, like <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> ſhe was without allowed guile, had the Teſtimony of her Conſcience, that in ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and Godly ſincerity, ſhe had her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in the World; very zealous for the truth of Jeſus Chriſt, following the Lamb whitherſoever he went.</p>
                  <p>She had <hi>a very publick Spirit,</hi> minding the good of others where ſhe lived; much taken up about the welfare of the Nation, and was deeply concerned for the intereſt of Chriſt all the world over, daily bore Zion, and the work that God was doing in the world upon her heart, and laid out her ſelf much in Prayer for thoſe things.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102520:74"/>
                  <p>She had <hi>a large heart for Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and for all that were his, though of differing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, always putting the beſt conſtruction upon every thing but ſin, was no way cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or ready harſhly to judge others, but did moſt fairly couſtrue their actions and carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, ſpeaking modeſtly, and moderately of them, Goſpel Charity ruling her Spirit in all, wonderful affable, and courteous, ſo as the Grace and ſweetneſs in her words and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, did win upon all that ſhe converſed with, that they loved her, and ſaid that ſhe was made up of love.</p>
                  <p>She by Grace <hi>was enabled to Regulate her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections;</hi> had a choice poiſe continually upon her Spirit, that ſhe ſeldom or never roiled or was diſturbed, but walked in an even and compoſed frame, though none more ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, loving tender and affectionate than ſhe, yet were her affections always in order, and under command, free from exceſſive and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing paſſions, that do often put the ſtrings of the Spirits of moſt men and women out of tune; and ſo render them unfit for what they are called too, in the place wherein the Lord hath ſet them.</p>
                  <p>She had <hi>a freſh remembrance of the means, and methods of the Lords dealing with her</hi> in bringing her Soul unto him, and of her many experiences ſhe had of his grace and love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102520:74"/>
                  <p>She <hi>lived much in Communion with God,</hi> there was an unſpeakable intercourſe between God and her Soul every day. She would do nothing till ſhe had ſpread it before the Lord, and knew his mind, and in things not only ſmall but weighty; She had ſuch intimations from the Lord of his will, and his ſecret was ſo with her, as ſhe before hand knew the mind of God, becauſe God had told hereby his Spirit, for ſhe gave not over till he had ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pirit upon her Spirit, what was his pleaſure, what he would do, or what he would have done, and God did marvelouſly herein condeſcend to her, not once, but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, or from time to time; ſhe was far from Euthuſiaſme, but had ſuch intimacy with the Lord, that ſhe went daily to him for ſome word, ſome manifeſtation of himſelf to bear up her Spirit that day, and he gave in either a word of promiſe, or let out ſomething of his attributes to her, diſcovered of his Wiſdom, Power, Faithfulneſs, Allſufficiency, Unchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gableneſs, and the like, wherewith her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man was fed and ſtrengthned, and when her Family concerns were more, ſhe aroſe the earlier, and though attended with the greateſt weakneſs, yet always began the day with God, and would not omit the ſeaſons for private Communion with the Lord, neither indeed could ſhe live without them, they being the life of her Spirit.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102520:75"/>
                  <p>She lived in <hi>an eminent exerciſe of many gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Spirit.</hi> She was well inſtructed in the myſtery of the life of Faith, lived in a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dependance upon God for all, in her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fulneſs ſhe lived not upon the creature but upon God, and recieved all from him in the way of Faith and Prayer, in every ſtrait ſhe had recourſe to the Al-ſufficiency of God, and would often ſay, <hi>the creature runs into empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the ſtreams they dried up, but the Fountain was ever full and flowing,</hi> and in all loſſes and changes bleſſed her ſelf in God her portion, who was a faithful Covenant, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God for ever; ſhe went to the Wiſdom of God to be directed, and waited there for Counſel every day, her faith advanced into aſſurance of the love of God which ſhe enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt part of her days, and thence iſſued ſpiritual and unmixed comforts: as ſhe walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed circumſpectly being careful not to provoke the Lord, ſo he witneſſed his love to her, and filled her Soul with ſtrong Conſolation, that ſhe had a Heaven out of it's place, even here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Earth, ſhe was in the Banquetting houſe of Jeſus Chriſt, in his Wine Cellar, where his Banner over her was Love. In a Letter of her own ſhe ſaid; I have not only heard that God is good, but I have had many experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Love and Faithfulneſs to me in all my ſtreights, and Widdow-hood condition: I may ſay the Life of Faith is the ſweeteſt Life in the World, as it is a Life that bringeth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102520:75"/>much glory to God, ſo much comfort to our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>How <hi>full of Love ſhe was to Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is already manifeſted in her carefulneſs to keep his Commandments, and alſo in her love to the Members of Chriſt, both that and alſo her Humility, and ſelf-denyal appeared in that, in her higheſt actings and beſt frame ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned her ſelf, and leaned only upon Jeſus Chriſt, truſted only in him, gloried in nothing but in Chriſt, in the Croſs of Chriſt, in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, in the Love of Chriſt: not in what ſhe did for Chriſt, though ſhe did much, and delighted in ſo doing, but ſhe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Grace of Chriſt that did much for her, he and his Righteouſneſs were all her life and comfort, ſhe had an eye upon the Incenſe, the merits and interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt in all her approaches to God, being aſhamed of the mixture of ſin, thoſe weakneſſes and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections that were in her beſt performances; notwithſtanding all her ſtrictneſs and exactneſs, ſhe lay as low before the Lord in the ſenſe of her own vileneſs, emptineſs, nothingneſs, as if there were nothing in her.</p>
                  <p>She was much in exalting of Jeſus Chriſt, his merits and grace, admiring what he had done for ſinners, touching their reconciliation to God, the remiſſion of ſin, their ſtanding and priviledges in grace here, and the glory that is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102520:76"/>to be revealed, relying on the freeneſs and fulneſs of his grace alone, as if ſhe had done or were able to do nothing, ſhe did ſet the Crown on his head in all, always ſaw that in her ſelf which kept her low and humble before the Lord, and nothing in her own eyes.</p>
                  <p>She excelled in, and was <hi>a pattern of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> under all her troubles, her afflictions were many and long, often at the very mouth of the Grave, in the latter part of her time ſeldom enjoyed a well day, yet never murmured; thought her afflictions ſmall, bore them with a chearful Spirit; was always ſubmiſſive to the will of God, always thought and ſpoke well of God, and juſtified him in all her Tryals.</p>
                  <p>She was wonderfully melted into the will of God, and lived always out of her own will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned up to God, to be diſpoſed of as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and was greatly ſatisfied in what he choſe for her, ſhe hath ſaid, the will of God is ſweet to her in every condition, and under much bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily weakneſs, <hi>if the Lord would have her live to be ſick ſhe was content,</hi> yet latter ward was moſtly tryed in the Fire of affliction, when her Husband laid down his living upon the accompt of Non-conformity in ſtead of repining, ſhe ſaid ſhe was glad they had ſuch a houſe, and accommodations to leave for Chriſt, and with all freeneſs and readineſs reſigned up all to him. She was ſorely tryed in the loſs of her deareſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102520:76"/>Relations and choiceſt comforts in this World, but ſhe was prepared to be any thing that God would have her be, and that with all alacrity and cheerfulneſs of Spirit.</p>
                  <p>She had a lively hope of future mercy; of the life to come: ſhee ſaid ſhe ſcarce knew how to live out of Heaven, from Jeſus Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways groaning in the body, to be delivered from the body of ſin and death, and to be with Jeſus. As ſhe ſet out at firſt, ſo ſhe continued in the vigorous and conſtant exerciſe of all grace, not looſing the life, nor abating or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing the ſtrength thereof in old age, under the decays of nature, but in the 73 of her age, ſhe ſlept or dyed in Jeſus, and her Soul was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:77"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:77"/>
                  <head>Books to be Sold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurst,</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Hundred ſelect Sermons on ſeveral Texts, by <hi>Tho. Horton,</hi> D. D.</p>
                  <p>Sermons on 4 ſelect <hi>Pſalms,</hi> viz. 4th. 42, 51, 63. by <hi>Tho. Horton,</hi> D. D.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Chriſtian Directory.</p>
                  <p>Sermons on the whole Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> by Mr. <hi>J. Daille,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>F. S.</hi> with Dr. <hi>Tho. Goodwins,</hi> and Dr. <hi>John Owens</hi> Epiſtles Recommendatory.</p>
                  <p>An Expoſition of Chriſts Temptation on <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. and <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon to <hi>Cornelius;</hi> and circumſpect walking, By Dr. <hi>Tho Taylor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Practical Expoſition on the 3d. Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> with the <hi>Godly mans choice,</hi> on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 4. v. 6, 7, 8. by <hi>Anthony Burgeſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Donns</hi> 40 Sermons, being his 3 Volumes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pareus</hi> Expoſition on the <hi>Revelations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>General Martyrologia, with the Lives of 32 Engliſh Divines, by <hi>Sam. Clark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Narrative of the Horrid Popiſh Plot.</p>
                  <p>— A Narrative of <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Lane.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>— The Witch of Endor.</p>
                  <p>— Popes Ware-houſe. All four Publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102520:78"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Robert Jenneſon</hi> Eſq; His Narrative.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dugdales</hi> Narrative.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Tho. Dangerfields</hi> of the Sham Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Plot.</p>
                  <p>Smiths Account of the 14 Popiſh Malefactors in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Animadverſions on the 5 Jeſuits Speeches. The Excommunicated Prince, a Tragedy as it was acted by his Holineſſes Servants, By Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>William Bedlow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Proteſtant Conformiſt plea for moderation.</p>
                  <p>A Conference between a Benſalion Biſhop, and an Engliſh Doctor concerning Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
                  <p>A Caution to all Engliſh Proteſtants.</p>
                  <p>A Lenetive for the Clergie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Broughtons</hi> Works publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Books 4 <hi>to.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Door of Salvation opened by the Key of Regeneration, By <hi>George Swinnock.</hi> M. A.</p>
                     <p>An Antidote againſt Quakeriſm, by <hi>Stephen Scandret.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Expoſition of the five firſt Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> with uſefull obſervations thereupon, by <hi>William Greenhil.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Goſpel Covenant opened, by <hi>Pet. Bulkley.</hi> Gods holy Mind, touching matters Moral, which he uttered in ten Commandments: Alſo an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on the Lords Prayer, by <hi>Edward Elton,</hi> B. D.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:78"/>
                     <p>The fiery Jeſuit, or an Hiſtorical Collection of the riſe, encreaſe, doctrines and deeds of the Jeſuits, expoſed to view for the ſake of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Horologiographia optica;</hi> Dyaling, univerſal and particular, ſpeculative and practical; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Deſcription of the Court of Arts, by a new Method, by <hi>Sylvanus Morgan.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Regimen ſanitatis ſalemi,</hi> or the Regiment of Health, containing Directions and inſtructions for the guide and government of mans life.</p>
                     <p>A ſeaſonable Apology for Religion, by <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Pool.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Seperation no Schiſm, in anſwer to a Sermon preached before the Lord Mayor, by <hi>J. S.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Practical Divinity of the Papiſt diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to be deſtructive to true Religion, and mens Souls, by <hi>J. Clarkſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Caſe of Conſcience, <hi>viz.</hi> whether it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any perſon to act contrary to the opinion of his own Conſcience, formed from arguments that to him appear very probable, though not neceſſary or demonſtrative, by Dr. <hi>Collings.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Creatures goodneſs as they came out of Gods hand, and the good-mans mercy to the bruit-Creatures, in two Sermons, by <hi>Tho. Hodges.</hi> B. D.</p>
                     <p>Certain Conſiderations tending to promote Peace and Unity among Proteſtants.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mediocria,</hi> or the moſt plain and natural ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions which the Scripture offers, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Doctrines of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb facs="tcp:102520:79"/>of Election, Redemption, the Covenant, the Law and Goſpel, and Perfection.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Funeral Sermons,</head>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>James Janeway,</hi> by <hi>Nath. Vincent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lady <hi>Suſanna Keate</hi>'s, by <hi>Richard Kidder,</hi> M. A.</p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Cautons,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Henry Hurſt,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Nath. Vincent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Sorrels,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Benj. Smith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> by Mr. <hi>R. Bragg.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Newcomens,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Fairſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Thomas Vincents,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Slater.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Corbets,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Bakers,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Nath. Vincent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Marſhalls,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Tomlins.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Johnſons,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Loid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mrs. <hi>Fiſhers,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Scot.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Whittakers,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Anneſly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Wells,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Thomas Watſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Stubs,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Watſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Stubs,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hodges</hi> Vanity of man as mortal.</p>
                     <p>Mrs. <hi>Lyes,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Lamb.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vertuous</hi> Daughter by <hi>Brion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Viners</hi> by Dr. <hi>Spurſlow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Perns,</hi> by <hi>Ainſworth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Work and Reward of a Chriſtian, by <hi>R. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Weſts</hi> Funeral Sermon, by Mr. <hi>Cole.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Webbs,</hi> by Mr. <hi>David Burges.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:79"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baxters</hi> which is the true Church;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hodges</hi> Creatures goodneſs.</p>
                     <p>Naked Truth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Doolitles</hi> Proteſtants Anſw. to a Popiſh Queſt.</p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Kidders</hi> Charity directed.</p>
                     <p>Scholars addreſs againſt Pluralities.</p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Croſſmans</hi> Sermon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Humphrys</hi> peaceable diſquiſitions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hodges</hi> conſiderations to promote peace.</p>
                     <p>An Endeavour for Peace; among Proteſtants.</p>
                     <p>A conference between a Papiſt and a Jew; and a Proteſtant and a Jew.</p>
                     <p>An Eſſay for the Education of Gentlewomen.</p>
                     <p>A warning for Servants or the Caſe of Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Clark.</p>
                     <p>An Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Stilling fleets</hi> Sermon by the peaceable deſign.</p>
                     <p>A Diſcourſe of Pluralities.</p>
                     <p>A Diſcourſe of Excommunication.</p>
                     <p>The middle way of Predetermination;</p>
                     <p>Popery an Enemy to Truth by Mr. <hi>Sheldreck</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Dumoulins</hi> conformity of Independent Government to the Antient Primitive Chriſtians.</p>
                     <p>Excommunication Excommunicated in a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogue between a Doctor of both Laws.</p>
                     <p>The Caſe of the Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> under a Popiſh Prince.</p>
                     <p>A rebuke to Informers.</p>
                     <p>A modeſt Inquiry into Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical miſtakes.</p>
                     <p>The State of Bleſſedneſs.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:80"/>
                     <p>An Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Stillingfleets</hi> Book by <hi>J. H.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Liberty of Conſcience in order to univerſal peace.</p>
                     <p>The Lords voice crying to <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Life of <hi>Herod</hi> the Great.</p>
                     <p>A Manifeſto, or an Account of the State, and differences between the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Sleſmick.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phelps</hi> Innocencies reward.</p>
                     <p>Materials for Union.</p>
                     <p>A ſheet of Union.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Roſſes</hi> Meſtogogus Poaeticus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phelps</hi> on the Revelations.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gilaſpys</hi> Ark of the Covenant.</p>
                     <p>Preſent State of New <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Collings</hi> of Providence.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Froyſells</hi> Sermons of Grace and Temptations.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Yarringtons</hi> Englands Improvement, Firſt part.</p>
                     <p>— Idem ſecond part.</p>
                     <p>Meaning of the Revelation, by <hi>John Hayter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Morning-Lecture againſt Popery, or the principal errors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and confuted in a Morning-Lecture, preached by ſeveral Miniſters of the Goſpel in or near <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Four uſeful diſcourſes: (1) The art of impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a full and proſperous condition for the glory of God; being an appendix to the art of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment in three Sermons, on <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.12. (2) Chriſtian ſubmiſſion, on 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Philip.</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:102520:80"/>1.21. (4) The Goſpel of peace ſent to the ſons of peace, in ſix Sermons, on <hi>Luke</hi> 10.5, 6. by <hi>Jeremiah Burroughs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Wilds</hi> Letter of Thanks and Poems.</p>
                     <p>A new Copy-Book of all ſorts of uſeful hands.</p>
                     <p>The new World; or new reformed Church, by Doctor <hi>Homes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Vertuous Daughter, a Funeral Sermon, by Mr. <hi>Brian.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Miracle of Miracles, or Chriſt in our Nature: by Dr. <hi>Rich. Sibbs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The unity and eſſence of the Catholick Church viſible, by Mr. <hi>Hudſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brightman</hi> on <hi>Revelations, Canticles</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Canaans</hi> Calamity.</p>
                     <p>The intercourſe of Divine Love between Chriſt and the Church, or the particular Beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul: in ſeveral Lectures on the whole ſecond Chap. of Cant. by <hi>John Collins,</hi> D. D.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Large 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The ſure mercies of <hi>David</hi> by <hi>Nath. Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Heaven or Hell here in a Good or Bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, by <hi>Nath. Vincent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Cloſet-Prayer a Chriſtians duty; all three by <hi>O. Heywood.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A practical diſcourſe of Prayer; wherein is handled the nature and duty of Prayer, by <hi>Tho. Cobbet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:81"/>
                     <p>Of quenching the Spirit; the evil of it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect both of its cauſes and effects, diſcovered; by <hi>Theophilus Polwheile.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſure way to Salvation; or a Treatiſe of the Saints myſtical Union with Chriſt; by <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Stedman.</hi> M. A.</p>
                     <p>Sober Singularity, by the ſame Author.</p>
                     <p>Heaven taken by Storm. by <hi>Tho. Watſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Childs Delight; together with an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Grammar.</p>
                     <p>Reading and Spelling made eaſie; both by <hi>Tho. Lye.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fables, with morals thereupon in Engliſh Verſe.</p>
                     <p>The Young-mans Inſtructor, and the Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans remembrancer; being an Explanation of the Aſſemblies Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>Captives bound in Chains, made free by Chriſt their Surety; both by <hi>Tho. Doolittle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Eighteen Sermons preached upon ſeveral Texts of Scripture, by <hi>William Whitaker.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Saints care for Church Communion; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in ſundry Sermons, preached at St. <hi>James Dukes-place,</hi> by <hi>Zech. Crofton.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The life and death of <hi>Edmund Stanton</hi> D. D. To which is added a Treatiſe of Chriſtian-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; and a Dialogue between a Miniſter and a Stranger.</p>
                     <p>Sin the Plague of plagues, or ſinful ſin the worſt of Evils; by <hi>Ralph Venning.</hi> M. A.</p>
                     <p>Caſes of Conſcience practically reſolved; by <hi>J. Norman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:81"/>
                     <p>The faithfulneſs of God conſidered and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the great Events of his Word; or a ſecond part of the fulfilling of the Scripture.</p>
                     <p>The immortality of the Soul explained and proved by Scripture and Reaſon; to which is added Faiths-triumph over the fears of death; by <hi>Tho. Wadſworth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Treatiſe of the incomparableneſs of God, in his Being, Attributes, Works, and Word; by <hi>George Swinnock,</hi> M. A.</p>
                     <p>A diſcourſe of the original, &amp;c. of the <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The generation of Seekers; or the right manner of the Saints addreſſes to the throne of Grace, with an Expoſition on the Lords-Prayer.</p>
                     <p>The adminiſtration of Cardinal <hi>Ximones.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Eſſay to facilitate the Education of Youth, by bringing down the rudiments of Grammar to the ſenſe of ſeeing which ought to be improved by <hi>Syncriſis;</hi> by Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Totenham.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Artificial Veſtibulum; wherein the ſenſe of <hi>Janua Linguarum</hi> is contained, compiled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to plain and ſhort ſentences in Engliſh, for the great eaſe of Maſters, and Expeditious progreſs of Scholars, by <hi>M. Lewis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Speculum Sherlockianum,</hi> or a Looking glaſs, in which the admirers of Mr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> may behold the man, as to his Acuracy, Judgment, Orthodoxy.</p>
                     <p>A diſcourſe of Sins of Omiſſion; wherein is diſcovered their Nature, Cauſes, and Cure; by <hi>George Swinnock.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:82"/>
                     <p>His Majeſties Propriety in the Britiſh Seas vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated.</p>
                     <p>Quakeriſm no Chriſtianity; or a through-Quaker no Chriſtian, proved by their Princr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and confirmed by Scripture; by <hi>J. Faldo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Differences about Water-baptiſm no bar to Communion; by <hi>Jo. Bunian</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi>-diſpenſatory; ſhewing the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, qualities and properties of Simples; the vertue and uſe of Compounds; whereto is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Compleat Herbaliſt.</p>
                     <p>Judg <hi>Dodaridge's</hi> laws of Nobility and Peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dinglys</hi> Spiritual Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>Solitude improved by Divine Meditation; by <hi>Matth. Ranew.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Murderer puniſhed and pardoned, or <hi>Tho. Savage</hi> his life and death; with his Funeral ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hurſt</hi> Revival Grace.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Buryes</hi> Husbandmans Companion.</p>
                     <p>— help to holy walking;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hanmers</hi> view of Antiquity,</p>
                     <p>Nomenclaturas.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Waſes</hi> Grammar.</p>
                     <p>Vincent of Conſcience.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gouges</hi> Principles of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
                     <p>— Chriſtian Direction.</p>
                     <p>— Word to Saints and Sinners.</p>
                     <p>— Young mans guide.</p>
                     <p>— Chriſtian Houſholder.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:82"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Perrots</hi> Englands duty.</p>
                     <p>The Nonconformiſts vindicated.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wadſworths</hi> remains.</p>
                     <p>Shepherdy Spiritualized.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calamys</hi> Art of divine Meditation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Faldos</hi> Quakeriſm no Chriſtianity.</p>
                     <p>— vindication of 21 Divines.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Small <hi>8vo.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A defence againſt the fear of death; by <hi>Zach. Crofton.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gods Soveraignty diſplayed, by <hi>William Gearing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Godly mans Ark, or a City of Refuge in the day of his diſtreſs, in five Sermons; with Mrs. <hi>Moors</hi> evidences for Heaven: by <hi>Edmund Calamy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Almoſt-Chriſtian diſcovered, or the falſe-Profeſſor tried and caſt, by <hi>M. Mead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The true bounds of Chriſtian-freedom: or a diſcourſe ſhewing the extent and reſtraints of Chriſtian-liberty, by <hi>S. Bolton,</hi> D. D.</p>
                     <p>The ſinfulneſs of Sin and fulneſs of Chriſt, in two Sermons; by <hi>Will. Bridg.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Plea for the godly, or the Righteous mans Excellency.</p>
                     <p>The holy Euchariſt, or the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
                     <p>A Treatiſe of ſelf-denial. All three by <hi>Tho. Watſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The life and death of <hi>Tho. Wilſon</hi> of <hi>Maidſtone</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:83"/>
                     <p>The Life and Death of Dr. <hi>Samuel VVinter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Covert from the Storm, or the fearful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in the day of Trouble.</p>
                     <p>Worthy-walking preſs'd upon all that have heard the Call of the Goſpel.</p>
                     <p>The Spirit of Prayer. All three by <hi>Nath. Vincent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The inſeparable union between Chriſt and a Believer, by <hi>Tho. Peck.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A diſcourſe of Excuſes, ſetting forth the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and vanity of them, the ſin and miſery brought in by them, by <hi>John Sheffield.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Inviſible reality, demonſtrated in the holy life and triumphant death of Mr. <hi>J. Janeway.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Saints encouragement to diligence in Chriſts ſervice: both by Mr. <hi>James Janeway.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A diſcourſe concerning the Education of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Convivium Caeleste;</hi> a plain and familiar diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the Lords Supper; both by <hi>R. Kidder.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Saints perſeverance aſſerted in its Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive-ground againſt Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> by <hi>Tho. Danſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Wedding-ring fit for the Finger; by <hi>VVill. Secker.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Explanation of the ſhorter-Catechiſm of the Aſſembly of Divines; by <hi>Tho. Lye.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The life and death of <hi>Tho. Hall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Plea for the Non-Conformiſts, tending to vindicate them from Schiſm, by a Doctor in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:83"/>
                     <p>The flat oppoſition of Popery to Scripture; by <hi>J. N.</hi> Chaplain to a Perſon of Honour.</p>
                     <p>The Weavers Pocket book, or Weaving ſpiritualiz'd by <hi>J. C.</hi> D. D.</p>
                     <p>Two diſputations of Original ſin; by <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Hiſtory of Moderation.</p>
                     <p>The welcome Communicant.</p>
                     <p>The little-peace-maker diſcovering fooliſh Pride, the Make-bate.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Philadelphia;</hi> or a Treatiſe of Brotherly love; by Mr. <hi>Gearing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Reformation or Ruine, being certain Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.23, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. by <hi>Tho. Hotchkis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Riches of Grace diſplayed; to which is added the priviledge of Paſſive obedience; and 52 propoſals in order to help on Heart-humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; by <hi>VVill. Bagſhaw.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The parable of the great Supper opened in 17 Sermons, by <hi>John Crump.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A preſent for Teeming-women, by <hi>J. Oliver.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Non-conformity without Controverſie; by <hi>Benj. Baxter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Treatiſe of Cloſet-Prayer; by <hi>Richard Mayo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Religious Family; by <hi>Philip Lamb.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A diſcourſe of the prodigious Abſtinence of <hi>Martha Taylor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Index biblicus multi-jugus,</hi> or a Table of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture; wherein each of its Books, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and particular matters are diſtinguiſhed and Epitomized.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:84"/>
                     <p>The day of Grace, with the Converſion of a Sinner; by <hi>Nathanael Vincent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An eaſie and uſeful Grammer for the learning of the French Tongue, by Mr. <hi>Goſthead,</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman.</p>
                     <p>The Miners Monitor, or advice to thoſe that are employed about the Mines.</p>
                     <p>A Proteſtant Catechiſm for litte Children.</p>
                     <p>A Scripture Catechiſm, by <hi>Samuel Petto.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Catechiſm according to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nero Tragidea.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cornelianum dolium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wilſons</hi> Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Elenchuus motuum nuperorum in Anglia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cackaines</hi> Poems.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Croftons Foelix Scelus;</hi> or proſpering-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs provoking holy conference, by <hi>Zach. Crofton.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gramaticus Analyticus,</hi> by the ſame Author.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alexanders</hi> advice to his Son.</p>
                     <p>H. Excellency of Chriſt ſet forth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phelps</hi> Caveat againſt Drunkenneſs.</p>
                     <p>— Lamentation for the loſs of a good man.</p>
                     <p>— Antidote againſt deſperation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bury</hi> againſt Drunkenneſs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wadſworths</hi> laſt warning to Sinners.</p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Wilkinſons</hi> Counſels and Comforts to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Conſciences.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cappello</hi> and <hi>Bianco,</hi> a Romance.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calys</hi> Glimpſe of Eternity.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:84"/>
                     <p>Period of humane Life.</p>
                     <p>Defence of Period of humane Life, both writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Author of the whole Duty of man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Anſwer to the period of humane Life.</p>
                     <p>Survey Quakeriſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tho. Vincents</hi> Explication of the Aſſemblies Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vincent</hi> on <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>— On Converſion and day of Grace.</p>
                     <p>—Covert from ſtorm.</p>
                     <p>—Worthy Walking.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Parſons</hi> Letter to <hi>VVem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adams</hi> Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lambs</hi> New Years Gift</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Perks</hi> way to mend the World.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Burys</hi> Antidote againſt the fear of Death.</p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Corbets</hi> Kingdom, God among men, with a Tract of Schiſm.</p>
                     <p>Self-imployment in Secret, by <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Solomons Proverbs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Traughtons</hi> Popery, the grand Apoſtacy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Heywoods</hi> Chriſt diſplayed.</p>
                     <p>Biſhop <hi>Reignolds Meditations.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Edward Weſts</hi> Legacy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gerhard</hi> on Death.</p>
                     <p>Whole Duty of Youth.</p>
                     <p>Welcome Communicant.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ames</hi> Marrow Diuinity.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tho. Vincent</hi> againſt the Quakers, being the ſandy Foundation ſhaken.</p>
                     <p>A warning to young men, or <hi>Brinkhurſts</hi> Narrative.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:85"/>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Kidders</hi> help to ſmalleſt Children in their underſtanding of the Church-Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thomas Vincents</hi> Himns.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bartlet</hi> on the Sacrament.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Greens</hi> needful preparatory to the Lords Supper.</p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Collings</hi> of ordinary matter of Prayer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wilſons</hi> Childs Trade.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Scondrets</hi> Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sheffiields</hi> Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>Much in a little, or an abſtract of Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> plain Scripture-proof for Infants Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p>Some brief Directions for the improvement of Infants Baptiſm.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Books Twelves.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Drexellius</hi> Repoſitory.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Meads</hi> Spiritual Wiſdom.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nathanael Vincents</hi> little Childs Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>The duty of Parents towards their Children.</p>
                     <p>A little book for little Children.</p>
                     <p>A method and inſtruction for the Art of divine Meditation. All three by <hi>Tho. VVhite.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The conſiderations of <hi>Drexelius</hi> on Eternity.</p>
                     <p>The ſhadow of the Tree of Life, by <hi>M. M.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> newly tranſlated: more plain, ſmooth and agreeable to the Text than any heretofore.</p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Henry Lukin</hi>'s Life of Faith.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:102520:85"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
